<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A hundreth good pointes of husbandry lately maried vnto a hundreth good poynts of huswifery: newly corrected and amplified with dyuers proper lessons for housholders, as by the table at the latter ende, more plainly may appeare: set foorth by Thomas Tusser Gentle man, seruant to the right honorable Lorde Paget of Beudefert.</title>
            <author>Tusser, Thomas, 1524?-1580.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24373</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846789</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846789</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11778</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11778)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 363:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A hundreth good pointes of husbandry lately maried vnto a hundreth good poynts of huswifery: newly corrected and amplified with dyuers proper lessons for housholders, as by the table at the latter ende, more plainly may appeare: set foorth by Thomas Tusser Gentle man, seruant to the right honorable Lorde Paget of Beudefert.</title>
                  <author>Tusser, Thomas, 1524?-1580.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Denham?] In ædibus Richardi Tottylli cum priuilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1570.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC; the woodcut title-page border has "HD" in sill.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Home economics --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Agriculture --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11778:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11778:1"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>A hundreth good</hi> pointes of Huſbandry, lately maried vnto a Hundreth good poynts of Huſwifery: newly corrected and amplified with dyuers proper leſſons for Houſholders, as by the table at the latter ende, more plainly may appeare: <hi>Set foorth by Thomas Tuſſer</hi> Gentle man, ſeruant to the right <hi>honorable Lorde Paget</hi> of Beudeſert.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In aedibus Richardi Tottylli <hi>Cum priuilegio.</hi> Anno. <hi>1570.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:2"/>
                  <head>The Preface.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat lookeſt thou here for to haue?</l>
                     <l>Trim verſes, thy fanſie to pleaſe?</l>
                     <l>Of Surry (ſo famous) that craue,</l>
                     <l>Looke nothing but rudeneſſe in theſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhat other thing lookeſt thou then?</l>
                     <l>Graue ſentences herein to finde?</l>
                     <l>Such Chaucer hath twentie and ten,</l>
                     <l>Ye thouſandes to pleaſure thy minde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhat looke ye, I pray you? ſhewe what,</l>
                     <l>Tearmes painted with rethorike fine?</l>
                     <l>Of makers of Engliſhe looke that,</l>
                     <l>But neuer in me nor in mine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhat lookeſt thou then at the laſt?</l>
                     <l>Good leſſons for thee and thy wyfe?</l>
                     <l>Then kepe them in memorie faſt,</l>
                     <l>From youth, to the laſt of thy lyfe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhat looke ye for more in my booke?</l>
                     <l>Things nedefull in tyme for to come?</l>
                     <l>Elſe miſſe I of that I do looke,</l>
                     <l>If pleaſant thou findeſt not ſome.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:3"/>
                  <head>The commodities of huſbandrie.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let houſe haue to fill her,</l>
                     <l>Let land haue a tiller.</l>
                     <l>No dweller, what good doth the houſe for to ſtande?</l>
                     <l>What profite vnhabited, bringeth the land?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No labour, no meate,</l>
                     <l>No hoſt, dye in ſtreate.</l>
                     <l>No huſbandry vſed how ſoone ſhall we ſterue?</l>
                     <l>Houſe keping neglected, what comfort to ſerue?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ill father no gift,</l>
                     <l>No knowledge, no thrift.</l>
                     <l>The father an vnthrift, what hope to the ſonne?</l>
                     <l>The ruler vnſkilfull, howe quickly vndone?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As true as thy fayth,</l>
                     <l>Thus huſbandry ſaith.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The praiſe of huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie.</note>I Seme but a drudge, yet I paſſe any king,</l>
                     <l>To ſuch as can vſe mee great wealth I do bring.</l>
                     <l>Since Adam firſt liued, I neuer did dye,</l>
                     <l>When Noe was a ſea man there alſo was I.</l>
                     <l>The earth is my ſtore houſe, the ſea my fiſheponde:</l>
                     <l>What they haue to pleaſure with, is in my hand.</l>
                     <l>what hath any life, but I helpe to preſerue,</l>
                     <l>What thing without me, but is ready to ſterue?</l>
                     <l>In Woodland, or Champion, Citie or towne,</l>
                     <l>If I be long abſent, what falleth not downe?</l>
                     <l>If I be long preſent, what goodneſſe can want,</l>
                     <l>Though thinges at my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, were neuer ſo ſcant.</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch as do loue me (what neede to recite)</l>
                     <l>(Ye though of the pooreſt) who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make I not knight.</l>
                     <l>Great Kinges I do ſuccour, elſe wrong it would go:</l>
                     <l>The King of all kinges hath appointed it ſo.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:11778:3"/>
                  <head>To the right honorable and my ſpeciall good Lorde and maiſter the Lorde <hi>Paget of Beudeſert.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>T</hi> TIme trieth the truth in euery thing,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>H</hi> How euer man doth blaſe his mynde:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O</hi> Of woorkes, which beſt may profite bring.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>M</hi> Men apt to iudge be often blinde.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> As therefore truth in time doth craue:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>S</hi> So let this booke iuſt fauour haue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>T</hi> Take you my Lorde, and Maſter than,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>V</hi> Vnleſſe miſchaunce miſchaunceth me:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>S</hi> Such homely gift of me your man,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>S</hi> Since more in court I may not be.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> And let your prayſe wonne heretofore,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>R</hi> Remaine abrode for euermore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>M</hi> My ſeruing you, thus vnderſtand,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> And God his helpe, and yours withall,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>D</hi> Did cauſe good luck to take mine hande</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E</hi> Erecting one moſt like to fall.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>M</hi> My ſeruing you I know it was,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E.</hi> Enforced this to come to paſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Since being once at Cambrige taught,</l>
                     <l>Of Court tenne yeres I made aſſay.</l>
                     <l>No muſike then was left vnſought,</l>
                     <l>Such care I had to ſerue that way.</l>
                     <l>My ioy gan ſlacke, then made I chaunge,</l>
                     <l>Expulſed mirth, for muſike ſtraunge.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My muſike ſince hath bene the plough,</l>
                     <l>Entangled with ſome care among,</l>
                     <l>The gaine not great, the paine inough,</l>
                     <l>Hath made me ſing another ſong,</l>
                     <l>Which ſong if well I may auow,</l>
                     <l>No man I craue to iudge but you.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your ſeruant Thomas Tuſſar.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:4"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> Haue bene prayde</l>
                     <l>to ſhewe mine ayde,</l>
                     <l>in taking payne</l>
                     <l>not for the gaine,</l>
                     <l>but for good will</l>
                     <l>to ſhewe ſuch ſkill</l>
                     <l>as ſhewe I coulde:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That huſbandry</l>
                     <l>with huſwifery</l>
                     <l>(as Cocke and Hen</l>
                     <l>to Country men)</l>
                     <l>all ſtraungneſſe gone</l>
                     <l>might ioyne in one</l>
                     <l>as louers ſhould.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I truſt both this</l>
                     <l>perfourmed is,</l>
                     <l>and how that here</l>
                     <l>if ſhall appere,</l>
                     <l>that I by prouſe</l>
                     <l>to thy behouſe</l>
                     <l>haue brought to paſſe?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That ſuch as wiue,</l>
                     <l>and fayne would thriue,</l>
                     <l>may here be taught</l>
                     <l>almoſt for naught,</l>
                     <l>to iudge and ſpye</l>
                     <l>of huſbandrye</l>
                     <l>as in a glaſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What ſhould I gayne,</l>
                     <l>to ſhewe in vayne</l>
                     <l>my loſſes paſt,</l>
                     <l>that ran more faſt,</l>
                     <l>than running ſtreame,</l>
                     <l>from reame to reame,</l>
                     <l>that fleeth ſo ſwift:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For that I coulde</l>
                     <l>not get for golde</l>
                     <l>to teach me howe,</l>
                     <l>as this do you,</l>
                     <l>ſo playne a way</l>
                     <l>from day to day</l>
                     <l>to come by thrift</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What is a grote</l>
                     <l>(or twaine) to note,</l>
                     <l>once in thy lyfe</l>
                     <l>for man and wife,</l>
                     <l>to ſaue a pounde</l>
                     <l>in houſe and grounde</l>
                     <l>eche other weeke?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhat more for vvelth?</l>
                     <l>vvhat more for health?</l>
                     <l>vvhat nedeth leſſe,</l>
                     <l>runne Iacke helpe Beſſe,</l>
                     <l>to ſtay amiſſe</l>
                     <l>thou hauing this</l>
                     <l>not for to ſeeke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I doe not craue</l>
                     <l>more thanks to haue,</l>
                     <l>than gyuen to me,</l>
                     <l>al redy be:</l>
                     <l>but this is all</l>
                     <l>that ſuch as ſhall</l>
                     <l>peruſe this booke:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That for my ſake</l>
                     <l>they gently take</l>
                     <l>vvhat ere they finde</l>
                     <l>againſt their minde,</l>
                     <l>vvhen he or ſhe</l>
                     <l>ſhall minded be</l>
                     <l>thereon to looke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:11778:4"/>
                  <head>The deſcription of Huſbandrie.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>OF huſband doth huſbandrie challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that name,</l>
                     <l>of huſbandrie huſband doth likewiſe the ſame.</l>
                     <l>Where huſwife and huſwiferie ioineth with theſe,</l>
                     <l>there weith in aboundaunce is gotten with eaſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The name of a huſband, what is it to ſay?</l>
                     <l>of wife and of houſhold the bande and the ſtaye.</l>
                     <l>Some huſbandly thriueth that neuer had wyfe,</l>
                     <l>yet ſcarce a good huſband in goodneſſe of lyfe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The huſband is he that to labour doth fall,</l>
                     <l>the labour of him I do huſbandrie call.</l>
                     <l>If thrift by that labour be any way caught,</l>
                     <l>then is it good huſbandrie, elſe is it naught.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So houſholde and houſholdrie I do define,</l>
                     <l>for folke and the goodes that in houſe be of thine.</l>
                     <l>Houſkeping to them as a refuge is ſet,</l>
                     <l>which like as it is, ſo report it doth get.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus houſholde and huſwiferie louers muſt bee,</l>
                     <l>with huſband and huſwife: yea further we ſee,</l>
                     <l>Houſekeping and huſbandrie (if they be good)</l>
                     <l>muſt loue one another as coſins in bloud.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Ladder to thrift.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>1</head>
                     <l>TO take thy calling thankfully,</l>
                     <l>To ſhunne the path to beggery.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2</head>
                     <l>To grudge in youth no drudgerie,</l>
                     <l>To come by penny luckely.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:5"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3</head>
                     <l>To get more to it wittily.</l>
                     <l>To kepe thy gettings couertly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4</head>
                     <l>To ſpende at firſt but nigardly,</l>
                     <l>To lay for age continually.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>5</head>
                     <l>To hearke to profite earneſtly,</l>
                     <l>To currey fauell willingly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>6</head>
                     <l>To get good plot to occupie,</l>
                     <l>To ſtore and vſe it huſbandly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>7</head>
                     <l>To get good wyfe for company,</l>
                     <l>To liue in wedlock honeſtly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>8</head>
                     <l>To ſtore thy houſe with houſholdrie,</l>
                     <l>To make prouiſion thriftilie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>9</head>
                     <l>To ioyne to wyfe good family,</l>
                     <l>To kepe no more but nedefully.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>10</head>
                     <l>To gouerne houſhold ſkilfully,</l>
                     <l>To ſuffer none liue ydely.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>11</head>
                     <l>To courage wife in huſwifery,</l>
                     <l>To vſe well doers gentely.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>12</head>
                     <l>To buy and ſell with pollicie,</l>
                     <l>To meddle not with pylferie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>13</head>
                     <l>To kepe thy touch ſubſtancially,</l>
                     <l>To make thy bondes aduiſedly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>14</head>
                     <l>To vſe thy neighbour neighbourly,</l>
                     <l>To vſe no frende deceitfully.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>15</head>
                     <l>To take good heede of ſuretie,</l>
                     <l>To loue to liue at libertie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:11778:5"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>16</head>
                     <l>To hate to liue vnthriftylye,</l>
                     <l>To ſtop thy mouth fro periurie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>17</head>
                     <l>To winne thy foe by honeſtye,</l>
                     <l>To vndermine his ſubtiltie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>18</head>
                     <l>To aunſwer ſtraunger curteouſly,</l>
                     <l>To kepe thy doings ſecretly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>19</head>
                     <l>To do thy doings orderly,</l>
                     <l>To play the ſubiect ſubiectly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>20</head>
                     <l>To trouble no man wilfully,</l>
                     <l>To hinder no man wittingly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>21</head>
                     <l>To offer no man villany,</l>
                     <l>To ſtay a miſchiefe ſpedilye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>22</head>
                     <l>To kepe that thine is manfully,</l>
                     <l>To liue by al men quietly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>23</head>
                     <l>To thinke well in aduerſitie,</l>
                     <l>To do well in proſperitie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>24</head>
                     <l>To get good loue and amitie,</l>
                     <l>To helpe relieue the pouertie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>25</head>
                     <l>To kepe good hoſpitalitie.</l>
                     <l>To hate all prodigalitie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>26</head>
                     <l>To kepe thy ſelfe fro maladye,</l>
                     <l>To eaſe thy ſickneſſe ſpedely.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>27</head>
                     <l>Theſe be the ſteppes vnfaynedly,</l>
                     <l>To clymbe to thrift by huſbandry.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:6"/>
                  <head>XXiiii. Leſſons alwaies to be obſerued.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>1</head>
                     <l>GOd neuer ſent mouth, but he ſent it meate,</l>
                     <l>who doing his wil euer wanted to eate?</l>
                     <l>Loue God aboue al things, who althings doth giue,</l>
                     <l>ſhew loue to thy neighbour, and lay for to liue,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2</head>
                     <l>True wedlocke beſt is, for auoiding of ſinne,</l>
                     <l>the bed vndefiled much honor doth winne.</l>
                     <l>Though loue be in choſing farre better than golde,</l>
                     <l>let loue come with ſomewhat the better to holde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3</head>
                     <l>Where couples agree not is rancour and ſtrife.</l>
                     <l>where ſuch be together is neuer good life:</l>
                     <l>Where couples in wedlocke doe louely agree,</l>
                     <l>there foyſen remayneth if wiſedome there bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4</head>
                     <l>Who loketh to mary muſt lay to kepe houſe,</l>
                     <l>for loue may not alway be plaiyng with dowſe.</l>
                     <l>If Children increaſe and no houſe of thine owne,</l>
                     <l>what trouble it is, to thy ſelfe ſhalbe knowne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>5</head>
                     <l>Good huſbands that loueth good houſes to kepe,</l>
                     <l>be often full careful when others do ſlepe:</l>
                     <l>To ſpend as they may, or to ſtoppe at the furſt,</l>
                     <l>for running behinde hand, or feare of the wurſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>6</head>
                     <l>Then count with thy cofers when harueſt is in,</l>
                     <l>thy Cardes being tolde, how to ſaue or to winne:</l>
                     <l>Of tone of them both, if a ſauour we ſmell,</l>
                     <l>houſe keping is godly where euer we dwell.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>7</head>
                     <l>Make money thy drudge for to folow thy warke,</l>
                     <l>make wiſedome controller, good order thy Clarke:</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11778:6"/>
                     <l>Prouiſion Cater, and ſkill to be Cooke,</l>
                     <l>make Stewarde of all, penne, inke and thy booke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>8</head>
                     <l>Make hunger thy ſauſe as a medicine for helth,</l>
                     <l>make thirſt to be Butler as Phiſyke for wealth.</l>
                     <l>Make eye to be Vſſher, good vſage to haue,</l>
                     <l>make barre to be Porter to ſtoppe out a knaue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>9</head>
                     <l>Make Huſbandry Baylye, abroade to prouide,</l>
                     <l>make huſwiferie dayly at home for to guide.</l>
                     <l>Make Cofer faſt loked, thy treaſure to kepe,</l>
                     <l>make houſe to be ſuer the ſafer to ſlepe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>10</head>
                     <l>Make Bandog thy watchman to bark at a thief,</l>
                     <l>make courage (for like) to be capitaine chiefe,</l>
                     <l>Make trapdoore thy Bulwark, make Bell to begin,</l>
                     <l>make gunſtone and arrow ſhew who is within.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>11</head>
                     <l>The Huſband he trudgeth to bring in the gaines,</l>
                     <l>the Huſwife ſhe drudgeth refuſing no paines.</l>
                     <l>Though Huſband without be to count ye wot what</l>
                     <l>the Huſwife within is as nedefull as that.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>12</head>
                     <l>What helpeth in ſtore, to haue neuer ſo muche,</l>
                     <l>halfe loſt by ill vſage, ill huſwiues and ſuch?</l>
                     <l>So twenty lode buſhes cut downe at a clap,</l>
                     <l>ſuche hede may be taken ſhall ſtoppe but a gap.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>13</head>
                     <l>With ſom vpon Sundaies their tables do reke,</l>
                     <l>and halfe the weke after their dinners to ſeke:</l>
                     <l>At no time to much, but haue alway inough,</l>
                     <l>is houſholdly fare, and the guiſe of the Plough.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:7"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>14</head>
                     <l>Eche day to be feaſted what huſbandry worſe?</l>
                     <l>eche day for to feaſt is as ill for the purſe.</l>
                     <l>Yet meaſurely feaſting with neighbors among.</l>
                     <l>ſhall make thee beloued and liue the more long.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>15</head>
                     <l>Make handſomely all things as cauſe ye do ſee.</l>
                     <l>but builde not for glory that thinkeſt to thee:</l>
                     <l>Who fondly in doing conſumeth his ſtocke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>in thende for his doing doth get but a mocke</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>16</head>
                     <l>Spend none but thine own howſoeuer thou ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
                     <l>for bribing and ſhifting haue neuer good ende.</l>
                     <l>Tythe truely for all thing, with God do not wreſt,</l>
                     <l>the iuſt in his dealing God proſpereth beſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>17</head>
                     <l>At ſometime to borow eſteme it no ſhame,</l>
                     <l>if iuſtly thou kepeſt thy touch for the ſame.</l>
                     <l>Who quicke be to borow, and ſlow bee to pay,</l>
                     <l>their credit is naught go they neuer ſo gay.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>18</head>
                     <l>Who liuing but lendes? and be lended they muſt,</l>
                     <l>elſe forty yeares purchaſe might lye in the duſt:</l>
                     <l>But craftie and naughtie that deſperate are,</l>
                     <l>make many ful honeſt the worſer to fare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>19</head>
                     <l>Vſe <hi>Legem pone</hi> to pay at thy day,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oremus</hi> (to beare with thee) vſe not (I ſay)</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Preſta queſumus</hi> out at a grate,</l>
                     <l>of all other Collectes, the lender doth hate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>20</head>
                     <l>Leaue Princes affaires vntalked vpon,</l>
                     <l>and tende to ſuch doings as ſtandeth thee on.</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:11778:7"/>
                     <l>Although that thy ſubſtance be neuer ſo much,</l>
                     <l>delight not in paraſites, harlots, and ſuch.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>21</head>
                     <l>Kepe truely thy Saboth the better to ſpede,</l>
                     <l>kepe ſeruant fro gadding but when it is nede.</l>
                     <l>Kepe Fiſhe day and faſting day, when they do fall,</l>
                     <l>what cuſtome thou kepeſt let others kepe all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>22</head>
                     <l>Pay wekely thy workme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their houſholds to fede</l>
                     <l>pay quarterly ſeruants to buy what they nede.</l>
                     <l>Giue garment to ſuch as deſerue and no more,</l>
                     <l>leaſt thou and thy wife without garment do goe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>23</head>
                     <l>Beware raſkabilia ſlouthfull to wurke,</l>
                     <l>proloyners and filchers that loueth to lurke.</l>
                     <l>Away with ſuch lubbers ſo loth to take payne,</l>
                     <l>that ſpendeth a ſhilling for one peny gayne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>24</head>
                     <l>Good wife and good children, are worthy to eate,</l>
                     <l>good ſeruant, good labourer, earneth their meate.</l>
                     <l>Good friend, and good neighbour, that fellowly geſt</l>
                     <l>with welcome at al times ſhoulde haue of the beſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A hundreth good poyntes <hi>of huſbandrye.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ Auguſt.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>1</head>
                        <l>WHen harueſt is ended, take ſhip or go ryde,</l>
                        <l>for ſaltfiſh and ſtockfiſh for Lent to prouide.</l>
                        <l>To buy them at firſt as they come to the rode,</l>
                        <l>ſhall pay for thy charges thou ſpendeſt abrode.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:8"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>2</head>
                        <l>Chooſe wiſely thy ſaltfiſh not burnt at the ſtone,</l>
                        <l>buy ſuch as be good, or elſe let them alone:</l>
                        <l>Get home that is bought, and go ſtacke it vp dry,</l>
                        <l>with peaſe ſtrawe betwene it the ſaffer to lye.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>3</head>
                        <l>(Thou going abroad) bid thy folke to make ſpede,</l>
                        <l>to compeſt thy Barley land when it is nede:</l>
                        <l>One acre wel compeſt, excedeth ſome three,</l>
                        <l>thy Barne ſhal at harueſt declare it to thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>4</head>
                        <l>This good ſhalbe learned by riding about,</l>
                        <l>the prices of vitailes, the yeare thoroughout:</l>
                        <l>Both what to be ſelling, and what to refraine,</l>
                        <l>and what for to buy, to be likely to gaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>5</head>
                        <l>Though buying and ſelling, doth wonderfull well,</l>
                        <l>to him that hath knowledge to buy and to ſell:</l>
                        <l>Yet chopping and changing I can not commende,</l>
                        <l>with knaue and his felow, for feare of ill end.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>6</head>
                        <l>The riche in their bargaining nede not be taught,</l>
                        <l>of feller and buyer fro farre they be taught:</l>
                        <l>Yea herein conſiſteth a part of the text,</l>
                        <l>who buyet at firſt hand, and who at the next.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>7</head>
                        <l>At firſt hand he buyeth that paieth all downe,</l>
                        <l>at ſeconde that hath not ſo much in the towne,</l>
                        <l>At thirde hand he buyeth that all borow muſt,</l>
                        <l>at his hand who buyeth ſhall pay for his luſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>8</head>
                        <l>As oft as ye bargaine for better or wurſe,</l>
                        <l>let alway one bargaine remaine in the purſe.</l>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:11778:8"/>
                        <l>Good credite doth well, but thy credite to kepe,</l>
                        <l>is pay and diſpatch him or euer ye ſlepe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>9</head>
                        <l>Be mindefull abroade of the Mihelmas ſpring,</l>
                        <l>for thereon dependeth a huſbandly thing.</l>
                        <l>When ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tles vſe walking w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Haukes on their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds,</l>
                        <l>good huſbands by graſing do purchaſe their landes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>10</head>
                        <l>Thy market diſpatched turne home again round,</l>
                        <l>leaſt gaping for peny thou loſeſt a pound.</l>
                        <l>Prouide for thy wife (elſe looke to be ſhent)</l>
                        <l>good milchcow for Winter, an other for Lent.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>11</head>
                        <l>In trauailing homewarde, buy .xl. good Crones.</l>
                        <l>and fat vp the bodies of thoſe ſely bones.</l>
                        <l>Leaue milking &amp; dry vp olde Mulley thy Cowe,</l>
                        <l>the crooked and aged to fatting put nowe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>12</head>
                        <l>Get downn w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy brakes, ere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhowers do come,</l>
                        <l>that cattel the better may paſture haue ſome.</l>
                        <l>In Iune and in Auguſt, as wel doth appeare,</l>
                        <l>is beſt to mowe Brakes, of all times in the yeare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Wife plucke fro thy karle, thy fimble hempe clene,</l>
                        <l>this looketh more yellowe, the other more grene.</l>
                        <l>Take this to thy vſage, leaue Michel the other,</l>
                        <l>for ſhoethreede, for halter, for rope and ſuch other.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ While wormwood hath ſede, get a bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>del or twaine</l>
                        <l>to ſaue againſt March, to make flea to refraine.</l>
                        <l>Wher cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber is ſwept, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wormewood is ſtrowne,</l>
                        <l>no flea for his life, dare abide to be knowne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:9"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Get gryeſt to the Mill, to haue plenty in ſtore.</l>
                        <l>leaſt Millers lacke water as many do more.</l>
                        <l>The meale the more yealdeth, if ſeruant be true,</l>
                        <l>if Miller that tolleth take noue but his due.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Pare Saffron betwene the two ſaint Mary daies</l>
                        <l>or ſet, or go ſhift it, that knoweſt the waies:</l>
                        <l>What yeare will ye ſhift it, the better to yelde?</l>
                        <l>the fowerth in the gardeyne, the thirde in the fielde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ In hauing but fortie foote cunningly dight,</l>
                        <l>take Saffron enough for the houſe of a knight.</l>
                        <l>All winter time after (as practiſe doth teache)</l>
                        <l>what plot can be better thy linnen to bleahce.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>13</head>
                        <l>Som ploweth, ſome burneth their wheat ſtubble lowe</l>
                        <l>ſome after their barley, lay wheat for to ſowe.</l>
                        <l>Which euer thou mindeſt, now time it is beſt,</l>
                        <l>elſe ſpare it for Cattel and ſo let it reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>14</head>
                        <l>Some vſeth the firſt yeare his fallow to make,</l>
                        <l>the next to ſowe Barley the better to take:</l>
                        <l>The third yere his peaſon, the ſame yere his wheate,</l>
                        <l>then fallow againe or to paſture for neate.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>15</head>
                        <l>Still crop vpon crop many farmours do take,</l>
                        <l>and gaine little money for gredyneſſe ſake,</l>
                        <l>Though wheat after Barley a cropper be found,</l>
                        <l>no cropper count Peaſe but a comfort to ground.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>16</head>
                        <l>Ere winter doth come while the wether is good,</l>
                        <l>for gutting thy paſture, get home with thy wood.</l>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:11778:9"/>
                        <l>Now cary thy grauell to fill vp a hole,</l>
                        <l>thy tymber, thy furzen, thy turffe, and thy cole.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>17</head>
                        <l>Houſe ſedges and turffe, chip and cole of the land</l>
                        <l>pyle tallwood and billet, ſtacke all that hath band.</l>
                        <l>Roote, block, pole &amp; bough, ſet vpright to the thetche,</l>
                        <l>the nerer more handſome in winter to fetch.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>18</head>
                        <l>At Bartilmew tide, or at Sturbrege faire,</l>
                        <l>buy all thing that needeth thy houſe to repaire.</l>
                        <l>Then ſell to thy profite thy butter and cheſe,</l>
                        <l>who ſelleth it ſohner, the more he doth leſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ September.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>19</head>
                        <l>THreſh ſede &amp; to fanning, the plough may not lie</l>
                        <l>September doth bid ye be ſowing of Rie.</l>
                        <l>Go harrow the ridges, ere euer ye ſtrike,</l>
                        <l>this point of good huſbandry Suffolke doth like.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>20</head>
                        <l>Take hede to thy man in his fury and heate,</l>
                        <l>with whipſtock &amp; ploughſtaffe for maiming thy neat</l>
                        <l>To threſher for hurting thy beaſt with his flaile,</l>
                        <l>or making thy hen to playe tapple vp taile.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>21</head>
                        <l>Sowe winter corne timely to follow his laſt,</l>
                        <l>ſowe wheat as ye may, but ſowe Rye in the duſt.</l>
                        <l>Be carefull for ſeede, or elſe ſuch as you ſowe,</l>
                        <l>looke iuſtly and ſurely to reape or to mowe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>22</head>
                        <l>Thy ſeede being ſowne, waterforow thy ground</l>
                        <l>that rayne when it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth may runne awaye round.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11778:10"/>
                        <l>Then out w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thy ſlinges, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thine arrowes &amp; bowes,</l>
                        <l>til ridges be greene, ſet a boy to kepe crowes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>23</head>
                        <l>Saint Mighel doth bid thee, ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thy marſhwal</l>
                        <l>the breck, and the crabhole, the foreland and all,</l>
                        <l>One noble in ſeaſon, beſtowed thereon,</l>
                        <l>may ſaue thee an hundreth, ere winter be gon.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>24</head>
                        <l>Go geld with the gelder, the Ram, and the bull,</l>
                        <l>buy Cattel for Rowen, ſell webſter thy wull.</l>
                        <l>Thy Hoppes go and gather, but not in the dewe,</l>
                        <l>and crabbes and thy walnuttes for feate of a ſhrew.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Now burne vp the Bees, of the Hiue that ye driue,</l>
                        <l>at Midſomer driue them and ſaue them aliue.</l>
                        <l>Allow them one cottage ſet Southly and warme,</l>
                        <l>and take for thy labour twiſe yerely a ſwarme.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>25</head>
                        <l>At Mighelmas ſafely, go ſtye vp thy Bore,</l>
                        <l>leaſt maſt being plentie, thou ſee him no more,</l>
                        <l>The leaner thou putteſt thy Bore into ſtye,</l>
                        <l>the ſounder he proueth, this proued haue I.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>26</head>
                        <l>To loke to thy maſt, it ſhal ſtand the vpon,</l>
                        <l>ſet ſeruants to gether, ere maſt be all gone.</l>
                        <l>Some left among buſhes, ſhal pleaſure thy ſwine,</l>
                        <l>for feare of a miſchiefe kepe Acornes fro Kine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>27</head>
                        <l>For rowting thy paſture, ring hogs thou haſt nede</l>
                        <l>which being well ringed, the better do fede.</l>
                        <l>The yong with the elder, will euer kepe beſt,</l>
                        <l>then yoke well the greateſt and fauour the reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:11778:10"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>28</head>
                        <l>Yoke neuer thy ſwyne, whyle the acorne do laſt,</l>
                        <l>for dyuers miſfortunes, that happen to faſt.</l>
                        <l>Or if that thou loueſt whole eare on thy hogge,</l>
                        <l>giue eye to thy neighbour, and eare to his dogge.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>29</head>
                        <l>The Moone in the wane, gather fruit on the tree</l>
                        <l>leſſe ſhaken more profite, for graffe, and for thee.</l>
                        <l>But Mychers that loue not to buy nor to craue,</l>
                        <l>make ſome gather ſooner, elſe fewe for to haue.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ October.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>30</head>
                        <l>THy Rie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground, while Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber doth laſt,</l>
                        <l>October for Wheat ſowing, calleth as faſt.</l>
                        <l>What euer it coſt thee, what euer thou geue,</l>
                        <l>haue done ſowing wheat, before Hallomas eue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>31</head>
                        <l>Get vp with the barley land, drye as ye can,</l>
                        <l>when euer ye ſowe it, ſo looke for it than.</l>
                        <l>Get alway before hand, be neuer behinde,</l>
                        <l>leaſt Winter preuenting, do hinder thy minde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>32</head>
                        <l>Sow Acornes ye owners, that Tymber do loue,</l>
                        <l>let Hawes be ſowen with them the better to proue.</l>
                        <l>If cattell or Cony, may come for to croppe,</l>
                        <l>no ſooner Oke commeth, but of goth his toppe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>33</head>
                        <l>When rayne will not let thee be doing abrode,</l>
                        <l>get flayle into Barne, and to threſhing good lode.</l>
                        <l>Threſh clene bid the threſhers, though leſſer thei earn</l>
                        <l>and (looking to thriue) haue an eye to the Barne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:11"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>34</head>
                        <l>If houſe rowme wil ſerue thee, lay ſtouer vp drie</l>
                        <l>and euery ſort by it ſelfe let it lye:</l>
                        <l>Or ſtacke it for litter if rowme be to poore,</l>
                        <l>and thetche out the reſidue for noying thy doore.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ Nouember.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l n="35">
                           <hi>35 A</hi> Thallomas ſlaughter time entereth in,</l>
                        <l>and then doth the huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmans feaſting begin:</l>
                        <l>From that tyme to ſhrouetyde, kil now &amp; then ſome,</l>
                        <l>their offall for houſholde the better ſhall come.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>36</head>
                        <l>Both Barley and bullimong, threſh out to mault.</l>
                        <l>let Maulter be cunning, elſe loſe it thou ſhalt.</l>
                        <l>Thincreaſe of a ſeame, is a buſhell for ſtore,</l>
                        <l>the Barly is bad or ſome filcheth the more.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>37</head>
                        <l>To winnow or fanne, which is better we ſwerue</l>
                        <l>but caſting is beſt if the flower will ſerue.</l>
                        <l>For ſeede go and caſt it, for mault do not ſo,</l>
                        <l>but get out the Cockle, and ſo let it go.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>38</head>
                        <l>Threſh Barley (as yet) but as nede ſhal require,</l>
                        <l>freſh threſhed for ſtouer, poore beaſt doth deſire.</l>
                        <l>And therefore that threſhing forbeare as ye can,</l>
                        <l>till Candlemas come, for to geue it them than.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>39</head>
                        <l>Saue chaffe of thy Barely, thy wheat &amp; thy Rie,</l>
                        <l>from byrd and from foyſtneſſe where it doth lie,</l>
                        <l>Firſt pike out the fethers, and ſift out the duſt,</l>
                        <l>then giue it thy horſes when labour they muſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:11778:11"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>40</head>
                        <l>Once euery weke, go make vp thy flower,</l>
                        <l>though ſlothfull and pilferer therat do lower.</l>
                        <l>Take tub for a ſeaſon, take ſacke for a ſhift,</l>
                        <l>yet ſoller for graine, is the beſt for thy thrift.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Set Gardeine Beanes after S. Edmond the king</l>
                        <l>the Mone in the wane, theron hangeth a thing,</l>
                        <l>Thincreaſe of a gallon, well proued of ſome,</l>
                        <l>ſhall pleaſure thy houſholde, or Peſcod do come.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>41</head>
                        <l>(For Eaſter) at Martilmas hang vp a beefe,</l>
                        <l>for Peaſe fed and ſtall fed, play pick purſe the theefe.</l>
                        <l>With that &amp; ſuch like, ere and graſſe beefe come in,</l>
                        <l>thy folke ſhall looke cherely, when others looke thin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>42</head>
                        <l>When plowing is done (and no paſture to eate)</l>
                        <l>then ſtable thy plough horſe, &amp; tend them with meat.</l>
                        <l>Let ſeaſon be drye when ye take them to houſe,</l>
                        <l>for daunger of nittes, or for feare of a louſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ December.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>43</head>
                        <l>WHen froſt will not ſuffer to dyke nor to hedge,</l>
                        <l>then get the an heat with thy Betle &amp; wedge.</l>
                        <l>Once Hallomas come, and a fyre in thy hall,</l>
                        <l>ſuch ſlyuers do well, for to lye by the wall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>44</head>
                        <l>Get grindſtone &amp; whetſtone to ſharpen thy toole</l>
                        <l>or elſe go and loyter, or let like a foole.</l>
                        <l>A Whelebarow alſo be ſure for to haue,</l>
                        <l>at hand of thy ſeruant thy compeſt to ſaue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:12"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>45</head>
                        <l>Geue cattle their fodder, the plot dry and warme,</l>
                        <l>and count them for myering, or other lyke harme.</l>
                        <l>Yong Coltes with thy wennels together go ſerue,</l>
                        <l>leaſt lurched by others, they happen to ſterue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>46</head>
                        <l>The racke I commende for the ſauing of dong,</l>
                        <l>ſo ſet as the olde cannot miſchiefe the yong.</l>
                        <l>If tempeſt be great, or the winde in the Eaſt,</l>
                        <l>warme barth vnder hedge, is a comfort to beaſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>47</head>
                        <l>Get truſtye to ſerue them, not lubberly ſquire,</l>
                        <l>that loueth all day to hang noſe ouer fire.</l>
                        <l>Nor truſt not to children thy cattel to feede,</l>
                        <l>but ſerue them let ſuch as may helpe at a neede.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>48</head>
                        <l>Serue firſt out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rye ſtraw, then wheat &amp; then peaſe</l>
                        <l>then ote ſtraw, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> barley, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hay if ye pleaſe.</l>
                        <l>But ſerue them with hay, while the ſtraw ſtoues laſt</l>
                        <l>they loue no more ſtraw, they had rather to faſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>49</head>
                        <l>Yoakes, forkes, &amp; the like let thy ſeruant ſpy out,</l>
                        <l>and gather the ſame, as he walketh about.</l>
                        <l>And after at leyſure let this bee his hyre,</l>
                        <l>to beath them, and make them, at home by the fyre.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>50</head>
                        <l>As well at the full of the moone, as at the change</l>
                        <l>ſea rages in winter, be often full ſtraunge.</l>
                        <l>Then looke to thy marches, if doubt be to fray,</l>
                        <l>for feare of <hi>Ne forte</hi> driue cattel away.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>51</head>
                        <l>Good fruit and good plentie, doth wel in thy loft,</l>
                        <l>then make thee an Orcharde and cheriſh it oft.</l>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:11778:12"/>
                        <l>For plant, and for ſtock, lay afore hand to caſt,</l>
                        <l>but ſet, or remoue it ere Chriſtmas be paſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>52</head>
                        <l>Set one from another ful twenty foote wide,</l>
                        <l>to ſtand as he ſtoode, is a parte of his pride.</l>
                        <l>The fayrer gotten, is beſt as ye knowe,</l>
                        <l>the deper ye ſet it, more likely to growe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>53</head>
                        <l>Ere Twelftide be gone, let thy horſe be let blood.</l>
                        <l>for diuers intentes, it ſhal do them much good.</l>
                        <l>The day of Saint Steuen, old huſbandes did vſe,</l>
                        <l>if that do miſlike the, ſome other daye chuſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>A digreſsion</head>
                     <l>LEaue huſbandrie ſleeping a while ye muſt do,</l>
                     <l>to learne of houſekeping a leſſon or two.</l>
                     <l>What euer is ſent thee, by traueile and payne,</l>
                     <l>a tyme there is lent thee, to ſpende it againe.</l>
                     <l>Though thou doſt defend it vnſpent for to bee,</l>
                     <l>another ſhal ſpende it, no thanke vnto thee.</l>
                     <l>How euer we climbe to accompliſhe the mynde,</l>
                     <l>we haue but a tyme, thereof profite to fynde.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>A deſcription of time <hi>and the yere.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OF God to thy doings a time there is ſent,</l>
                        <l>which endeth with time, that in doing is ſpent.</l>
                        <l>For tyme is it ſelfe but a time for a tyme,</l>
                        <l>forgotten full ſoone, as the tune of a chyme.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:13"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In ſpring time we reare, we do ſowe, ſet and plant,</l>
                        <l>in ſommer get vittels, leaſt after we want.</l>
                        <l>In harueſt we carry in corne and the fruit,</l>
                        <l>in winter to ſpende as we nede of eche ſute.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The yeare I compare as I finde for a truth,</l>
                        <l>the ſpring vnto childhode, the ſommer to youth.</l>
                        <l>The harueſt to manhode the winter to age,</l>
                        <l>all quickly forgotten as a playe on a ſtage.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tyme paſt is forgotten, ere men be aware,</l>
                        <l>tyme preſent is thought on with wonderful care.</l>
                        <l>Time comming is feared, and therefore we ſaue.</l>
                        <l>yet oft ere it come we be gon to the graue.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ A deſcription of lyfe <hi>and ryches.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHo lyuing, but daily diſcerne it he may,</l>
                        <l>how life as a ſhadow doth vaniſh away.</l>
                        <l>And nothing to count on ſo ſure and ſo iuſt,</l>
                        <l>as ſurely to dye, and to turne into duſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The landes and the riches that here we poſſeſſe,</l>
                        <l>be none of our owne, if a God we profeſſe.</l>
                        <l>But lent vs of him, as his talent of golde,</l>
                        <l>which being demaunded who can it witholde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>God maketh no wryting that iuſtly doth ſay.</l>
                        <l>how long we ſhal haue it, a yeare or a day:</l>
                        <l>But leaue it we muſt (how ſoeuer we liue)</l>
                        <l>when death ſhal come pluck vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence by the ſliue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:11778:13"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To death we muſt ſtoupe, be we high, be we lowe,</l>
                        <l>but how, and how ſodenly, fewe be that knowe.</l>
                        <l>what cary we then but a ſheete to the graue,</l>
                        <l>to couer this carkas, of al that we haue.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>A deſcription of <hi>houſe kepyng,</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, while here we remaine</l>
                        <l>but ſtudy to yelde it to God with a gaine?</l>
                        <l>And that ſhal we doe, if we do it not hide,</l>
                        <l>but vſe and beſtow it as God doth vs did.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What good to get ryches by breaking of ſlepe,</l>
                        <l>but (hauing the ſame) a good houſe for to kepe?</l>
                        <l>Not onely to bring a good fame to thy doore,</l>
                        <l>but alſo the prayer to winne of the poore.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Of all other doings houſe keping is chiefe,</l>
                        <l>for alway it helpeth the poore with reliefe.</l>
                        <l>The neighbor, the ſtraunger, &amp; al that haue nede,</l>
                        <l>which cauſeth thy doings the better to ſpede.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Though hearken to this we ſhould euer among,</l>
                        <l>yet chiefly at Chriſtmas of all the yeare long</l>
                        <l>Good cauſe of that vſe may appere by the name,</l>
                        <l>though ſuch as knowe leaſt diſaloweth the ſame,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>A deſcription of <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OF Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth Chriſtmas, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſte,</l>
                        <l>a time full of ioy to greateſt and leaſt.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11778:14"/>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas was Chriſt (our ſauior) borne,</l>
                        <l>the worlde through ſinne altogether forlorne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas the day doth begin to take length,</l>
                        <l>of Chriſt our faith doth begin to take ſtrength.</l>
                        <l>As Chriſtmas is onely a figure or trope,</l>
                        <l>ſo onely in Chriſt is the ſtrength of our hope.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas we banket the riche with the poore,</l>
                        <l>who then (but the Miſer) but openeth his doore?</l>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas of Chriſt, many Carols we ſing.</l>
                        <l>and giue many giftes, in the ioy of that king.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas in Chriſt, we reioyce and be glad,</l>
                        <l>as onely of whom our comfort is had.</l>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas we ioy altogether with mirth,</l>
                        <l>for his ſake that ioyed vs al with his birth.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>A deſcription of</hi> apt time to ſpend.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>LEt ſuch (ſo fantaſticall) liking not this,</l>
                        <l>(nor nothing elſe honeſt, that auncient is)</l>
                        <l>Giue place to the time that ſo apte we do ſee,</l>
                        <l>appointed of God, as it ſeemeth to bee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas good huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds haue corne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground</l>
                        <l>in Barne and in ſoller worth many a pound.</l>
                        <l>Things plenty in houſe (beſyde Cattel and ſhepe,</l>
                        <l>all ſent them (no doubt on) good houſes to kepe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas the hardneſſe of Winter doth rage.</l>
                        <l>a nipper of all thing in euery age.</l>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:11778:14"/>
                        <l>Then lightly poore people, the yong with the olde,</l>
                        <l>be ſoreſt oppreſſed with hunger and colde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas by labour is little to get,</l>
                        <l>that wanting the poore man in daunger is ſet.</l>
                        <l>What better a time than o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> al the whole yeare,</l>
                        <l>thy nedy poore neighbour to comfort and cheare.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Againſt fantaſticall <hi>ſcrupleneſſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AT this and at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing ſome make a great mater,</l>
                        <l>ſome help not, but hinder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their clatter.</l>
                        <l>Take cuſtome from feaſting what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth then, laſt</l>
                        <l>where one hath a dinner, a thouſand ſhal faſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To dog in the maunger, ſome liken I coulde,</l>
                        <l>that hay will eate none, nor let other that would.</l>
                        <l>Some ſcarce in a yere giue a dinner or two,</l>
                        <l>nor wel can abide any other to do.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Play thou the good felow and harken to me,</l>
                        <l>hate none that be honeſt, though mery they be.</l>
                        <l>For often times ſene, no more very a knaue,</l>
                        <l>than he that doth counterfet moſt to be graue.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Chriſtmas huſbandly fare.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>GOod huſband &amp; huſwife now (chiefly) be glad,</l>
                        <l>things ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſom to haue as they ought to be had</l>
                        <l>They both do ꝓuide againſt chriſtmas do com,</l>
                        <l>to welcom their neighbors, good chere to haue ſom.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11778:15"/>
                        <l>Good bread and good drink, a good fyre in the hall,</l>
                        <l>brawne pudding and ſouſe &amp; good muſtard withall.</l>
                        <l>Biefe, mutton, and porke, and good Pies of the beſt,</l>
                        <l>pig, veale, goſe and capon, and Turkey well dreſt.</l>
                        <l>Cheſe, apples &amp; nuttes, and good Charrols to heare,</l>
                        <l>as then in the contrey is counted good cheare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What coſt to good huſband is any of this?</l>
                        <l>good houſhold prouiſion onely it is.</l>
                        <l>Of other the like, I do leaue out a meny,</l>
                        <l>that coſteth the huſband neuer a peny.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>At Chriſtmas be mery and thankfull withall,</l>
                        <l>&amp; feaſt thy poore neighbors the great with the ſmall.</l>
                        <l>Yea al the yeare long to the poore let vs gine,</l>
                        <l>gods bleſſing to haue here as long as we liue.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ Ianuarye.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>54</head>
                        <l>WHen Chriſtmas is ended, bid feaſting adew,</l>
                        <l>go play the good huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, thy ſtock to renew.</l>
                        <l>Be myndefull of rearing, in hope of a gaine,</l>
                        <l>dame profit ſhal geue thee rewarde for thy payne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>55</head>
                        <l>Who both by his calfe, &amp; his lambe wil be known,</l>
                        <l>may well kill a neate, and a ſhepe of his owne.</l>
                        <l>And he that wil reare vp a pyg in his houſe,</l>
                        <l>hath cheaper his bacon, and ſweter his ſouſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>56</head>
                        <l>who eateth his veale, pig &amp; lambe being froath,</l>
                        <l>ſhall thriſe in a weeke go to bed without broath.</l>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:11778:15"/>
                        <l>Vnſkilfull that paſſe not but ſell away ſell,</l>
                        <l>ſhal neuer keepe good houſe where euer they dwell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>57</head>
                        <l>Be gredy in ſpending and careleſſe to ſaue,</l>
                        <l>and ſhortly be nedy and redy to craue.</l>
                        <l>Be wilfull to kill and vnſkilfull to ſtore,</l>
                        <l>and neuer looke long to keepe houſe any more.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>58</head>
                        <l>Lay dirt vpon heapes faire yarde to kepe ſene,</l>
                        <l>when froſt will abide, into fielde with it clene.</l>
                        <l>In winter a fallow ſome loue to beſtowe,</l>
                        <l>where peaſe for the pot they intende for to ſowe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>59</head>
                        <l>In making or mending, (as nedeth) thy ditch,</l>
                        <l>get ſet to quicke ſet it, learne cunningly which.</l>
                        <l>In hedging (where clay is) cut ſtake as ye knowe,</l>
                        <l>of Popler and Sallow, for fewell to growe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>60</head>
                        <l>Leaue killing of Cony, let Doe go to Bucke,</l>
                        <l>and vermine thy borrowe for feare of ill lucke.</l>
                        <l>Fede Doue (no more killing) old doue houſe repaire,</l>
                        <l>ſaue Doue dong for hopyard, in making holes faire.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Dig Gardain, ſtroy malow now may ye at eaſe,</l>
                        <l>and ſet (as as a deintie) thy runcyfall peaſe.</l>
                        <l>Go cut and ſet Roſes the beſt to be got,</l>
                        <l>of al the yeare long, better time there is not.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>61</head>
                        <l>In time go and bargaine leſt worſer do fall,</l>
                        <l>for fewell, for making, for cariage and all.</l>
                        <l>To buy at the ſtub, is the beſt for the buier,</l>
                        <l>more timely prouiſion, more cheaper the fyer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:16"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>62</head>
                        <l>Some burneth a load at a time in his Hall,</l>
                        <l>ſome neuer leaue burning, till burnt they haue all.</l>
                        <l>Some making hauock with out any wit,</l>
                        <l>make many poore ſoules without fier to ſit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>63</head>
                        <l>From Chriſtmas, till May be wel entered in,</l>
                        <l>al cattel wax faint, and looke poorely and thin.</l>
                        <l>But when as the prime graſſe, at firſt doth appeare,</l>
                        <l>then moſt is the daunger of all the whole yeare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Calues faire, that come betwene Chriſtmas &amp; Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
                        <l>take huſwife to rere, or elſe after repent.</l>
                        <l>Of ſuch as fall betwene chaunge and the prime,</l>
                        <l>no rering, but ſell, or go kill them in time.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Houſe Calfe, and go ſuckle it twiſe on a day,</l>
                        <l>and after a while ſet it water and hay,</l>
                        <l>Stake ragged to rubbe on, no ſuch as will bend,</l>
                        <l>then weane it (well tended) at fifty daies ende.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ The ſenior weaned, his yonger ſhall teach,</l>
                        <l>both how to drink water, and hay for to reach.</l>
                        <l>More ſtroke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, more made on, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought they do aile,</l>
                        <l>more gentle ye make them for yoke or to paile.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>64</head>
                        <l>Yong brome or good paſture, thine ews do <abbr>reqre</abbr>
                        </l>
                        <l>warme barth and in ſaftie their Lambes do deſire:</l>
                        <l>Looke often well to them for Foxes and dogges,</l>
                        <l>for pittes and for brimbles, for vermine and hogges.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>65</head>
                        <l>Geld bulcalfe &amp; ram lambe, as ſone as they fall,</l>
                        <l>for therin is lightly no daunger at all.</l>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11778:16"/>
                        <l>Some ſpareth the tone for to pleaſure the eye,</l>
                        <l>to haue him ſhew great when the butcher ſhall buy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Sowes ready to farow, this time of the yere,</l>
                        <l>are for to be made on and counted full deare.</l>
                        <l>For now is the loſſe of a fare of thy Sowe,</l>
                        <l>more great than the loſſe of two calues of thy Cow,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Of one Sow at once rere fewe aboue fiue,</l>
                        <l>and chooſe of the faireſt and likeſt to thriue.</l>
                        <l>Vngelt of the beſt kepe a couple for ſtore,</l>
                        <l>one Boare pig, one Sow pig, that ſucketh before.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>66</head>
                        <l>Geld vnder the dame within fortnight at leaſt,</l>
                        <l>and ſaue both thy money and life of thy beaſt.</l>
                        <l>Geld later with Gelders as many one do,</l>
                        <l>and looke of a dozen to geld away two.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>67</head>
                        <l>Thy Coltes for the ſaddle geld yong to be light.</l>
                        <l>for Cart do not ſo if thou iudgeſt aright.</l>
                        <l>Nor geld them but when they be luſty &amp; fat.</l>
                        <l>for there is a point to be learned in that.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>68</head>
                        <l>Geld Fillies but tittes, ere &amp; nine daies of age,</l>
                        <l>they dye elſe of gelding, elſe many do rage.</l>
                        <l>But Fillies moſt likely, of bulke and of bone,</l>
                        <l>kepe ſuch to bring Coltes, let their gelding alone.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>69</head>
                        <l>For gaining a trifle, ſell neuer thy ſtore,</l>
                        <l>what ioy to acquaintance what pleaſureth more?</l>
                        <l>More larger of body the better to brede,</l>
                        <l>more forwarde of growing, the better they ſpede.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:17"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>70</head>
                        <l>A Cowe good of milke that is faire and ſounde,</l>
                        <l>is yerely for profit as good as a pounde.</l>
                        <l>And yet by the yere haue I proued or now,</l>
                        <l>as good to the purſe, is a Sow as a Cowe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>71</head>
                        <l>Kepe one and kepe both with as little a coſt,</l>
                        <l>then al ſhalbe ſaued and nothing be loſt.</l>
                        <l>Both hauing together, what profit is taught,</l>
                        <l>good huſwiues I warrant ye nede not be taught,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Go looke to thy Bees if the hiue he to light,</l>
                        <l>ſet water and hony together well dight.</l>
                        <l>Put ſtrawes in a diſhe to the ſame in the hiue,</l>
                        <l>from daungers a number ye ſaue them aliue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>72</head>
                        <l>In Ianuary huſband that poucheth vp grotes,</l>
                        <l>will breake vp his lay or be ſowing of Otes.</l>
                        <l>Otes ſowen in Ianuary lay by the wheate,</l>
                        <l>in May by thy hay, for the cattel to eate.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ Februarye.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>73</head>
                        <l>NOw timely for Lentſtuffe, thy mony diſburſe,</l>
                        <l>the lenger thou tarieſt (for profit) the worſe.</l>
                        <l>If one peny vauntage be therin to ſaue,</l>
                        <l>of Coaſtman or Fleming now looke it to haue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>74</head>
                        <l>Thy Vines and thy Oſyers cut and go ſet,</l>
                        <l>if grape be vnpleaſant a better to get.</l>
                        <l>Feede Swan and go make hir vp ſtrongly a neſt,</l>
                        <l>for feare of a floud, good and highe is the beſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:11778:17"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>75</head>
                        <l>Go eare in thy ſtubble, take timely thy ſeaſon,</l>
                        <l>be ſowing of Beanes, thy Tares, and thy peaſon.</l>
                        <l>The ſooner thou ſoweſt, the ſooner they come,</l>
                        <l>and better for houſhold they fill vp a rome.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>76</head>
                        <l>White peaſon, both good for the pot &amp; the purſſe,</l>
                        <l>by ſowing to timely proue often the wurſſe.</l>
                        <l>Becauſe they be tender and hateth the colde,</l>
                        <l>proue Marche ere ye ſow them, then may ye be bold.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>77</head>
                        <l>In euery greene, if the fence be not thine,</l>
                        <l>go ſtub vp the buſhes, the graſſe to be fine.</l>
                        <l>Elſe neighbour will dayly ſo hacke them beliue,</l>
                        <l>that neither thy graſſe, nor thy buſhes ſhal thriue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>78</head>
                        <l>Go lop for thy fewell, the pollengers growen,</l>
                        <l>that hindreth the corne, or the graſſe to be mowen.</l>
                        <l>In lopping and cropping, ſaue edder and ſtake,</l>
                        <l>thine hedges, where neede is to mende or to make.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>79</head>
                        <l>In lopping olde Iocham, for feare of miſhap,</l>
                        <l>leaue one bough vnlopped to cheriſhe the ſap.</l>
                        <l>The ſecond yere after then boldly ye may,</l>
                        <l>for hindring his felowes, that bough cut away.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>80</head>
                        <l>The ſtickes &amp; the ſtones, go &amp; gather them clene,</l>
                        <l>for hurting thy Sithe, or for harming thy grene.</l>
                        <l>For walkers by Moone ſhine get home w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the reſt,</l>
                        <l>when frozen the grounde is then cariage is beſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>81</head>
                        <l>In cropping or felling, take hede to this thing,</l>
                        <l>be ſkilful and carefull for ſauing the ſpring.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11778:18"/>
                        <l>Leaue topping of timber for making of waſt,</l>
                        <l>leaſt landlord by law, doth auoide thee in haſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>82</head>
                        <l>Spare medows at ſhroftide, thy marſhes at paſk,</l>
                        <l>for feare of dry Sommer no lenger time aſke.</l>
                        <l>Then hedge them &amp; dych them, beſtow theron pence,</l>
                        <l>corne, medow, and marſhes, craue euer good fence.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>83</head>
                        <l>Frend, alway let this be a part of thy care,</l>
                        <l>for ſhift of good paſture, lay paſture to ſpare.</l>
                        <l>Then ſeauer thy groundes, and ſo keping them ſtill,</l>
                        <l>and cattell at eaſe, and haue paſture at will.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>84</head>
                        <l>Kill crow, pye, &amp; caddow, rooke, buſſard, &amp; rauen,</l>
                        <l>or elſe go deſire them to ſeeke a newe hauen,</l>
                        <l>In ſcalling the youg for to pluck of his becke,</l>
                        <l>beware how thou ſcaleſt for breaking thy neck.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ Marche.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>85</head>
                        <l>SOwe Barley in March, and in Aprill &amp; May,</l>
                        <l>the latter in ſand and the ſooner in claye.</l>
                        <l>What worſer for Barley, then wetneſſe and colde?</l>
                        <l>what thing to take time when a man may be bolde?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>86</head>
                        <l>Kepe Crowes and go harrow it finely as duſt,</l>
                        <l>then woorkmanly trench it, and fence it ye muſt.</l>
                        <l>This ſeaſon well handled, ſet ſowing an ende,</l>
                        <l>and praiſe and pray God, a good harueſt to ſende.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>87</head>
                        <l>Sowe wheat in a meaſure, ſowe Rie not to thin,</l>
                        <l>let Beanes and thy Peaſon be ſcatered in.</l>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:11778:18"/>
                        <l>Sow Barley &amp; Otes good and thick, do not feare,</l>
                        <l>land looketh for ſeede, or the weede for to beare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>88</head>
                        <l>Otes Barley and Peaſe, harowe after ye ſowe,</l>
                        <l>for Rye harrow firſt (not after I trowe.)</l>
                        <l>Leaue Wheate little clod for to couer his head,</l>
                        <l>that after a froſt he may forth and go ſpread.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>89</head>
                        <l>In March is good graffing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſkilful doth know.</l>
                        <l>as long as the winde in the Caſt doth not blow.</l>
                        <l>From Moone being chaunged, till paſt bee the prime,</l>
                        <l>for graffing and cropping is excellent time.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>90</head>
                        <l>Thinges ſowen ſet, or planted, the greateſt &amp; leaſt</l>
                        <l>defend againſt tempeſt, the birde, and the beaſt.</l>
                        <l>Defended ſhal proſper, the tother is loſt,</l>
                        <l>the thing with thy labour, the time and the coſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ In March and in Aprill, from morning to night,</l>
                        <l>in ſowing and ſetting good huſwiues delight.</l>
                        <l>To haue in their Gardeine or other like plot,</l>
                        <l>to trim vp their houſe, and to furniſh their pot.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ The vertue of herbes dame Phiſike doth ſhewe,</l>
                        <l>time teacheth them all to be knowen, ſaue a fewe.</l>
                        <l>To ſet or to ſowe, or once ſowne to remoue,</l>
                        <l>how this ſhould be learned, by practiſe go proue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Good Parſneps and Mellons, all Winter &amp; Lent,</l>
                        <l>Beanes plentie in Iuly, ſaue fiſhe to be ſpent.</l>
                        <l>Thoſe hauing with pottage the belly full than,</l>
                        <l>thou winneſt the hart of thy labouring man.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:19"/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ Aprill.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>FRom Aprill begin to ſaint Andrew be paſt,</l>
                        <l>ſo long with good huſwiues theire dayries do laſt.</l>
                        <l>Good leaſe &amp; good paſture, good huſbandes prouide,</l>
                        <l>the reſidue good huſwiues know how for to guide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Such huſwiues as knowe not to make their owne chees</l>
                        <l>with truſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of others haue this for their fees.</l>
                        <l>Milk flapped in corners, creame ſlabbred and ſoſt,</l>
                        <l>milk pan ſo nigh flot, that the cheſes be loſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Where ſome of a Cowe, do make yerely a pound,</l>
                        <l>with theſe fiely huſwiues, no peny is found.</l>
                        <l>The ſeruauntes rebuked for that they haue donne,</l>
                        <l>with one thing or other away they do roone.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Then neighbour for god ſake, if any you ſee,</l>
                        <l>good ſeruant for dairy, helpe wane her to mee.</l>
                        <l>Such maiſter ſuch man, &amp; ſuch Miſtreſſe ſuch maide,</l>
                        <l>ſuch huſband and huſwife, ſuch houſes araide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>91</head>
                        <l>Sell barke to the Tanner ere timber ye fell,</l>
                        <l>fell low by the ground, or elſe do ye not well.</l>
                        <l>In breaking ſaue croked for milles and for ſhippes,</l>
                        <l>and euer in hewing ſaue Carpenters chippes.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ May.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>92</head>
                        <l>FRo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> May til October leaue cropping, learn why,</l>
                        <l>in wood ſere what euer thou croppeſt will dye.</l>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:11778:19"/>
                        <l>Where Iuie embraceth the tree very ſore,</l>
                        <l>kill Iuie, or tree elſe will adle no more.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Good flaxe &amp; good hempe, for to haue of her owne,</l>
                        <l>good huſwife in May will ſee it be ſowne.</l>
                        <l>And afterward trim it to ſerue at a neede,</l>
                        <l>the fimble to ſpinne, and the karle for her ſede.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ The knowledge of ſtilling is one pretie feate,</l>
                        <l>the waters be holſome, the charges not great.</l>
                        <l>What timely thou getteſt, while Summer doth laſt,</l>
                        <l>thinke Winter will helpe thee to ſpende it as faſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ In May is good ſowing, thy buck or thy frank,</l>
                        <l>that blacke is as Pepper, and ſmelleth ſo ranke.</l>
                        <l>It is to thy land, as a comfort or mucke,</l>
                        <l>and all thing it maketh as fatt as a bucke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>93</head>
                        <l>At Phillip and Iacob, go put of thy lambes,</l>
                        <l>that thinkeſt to haue any milke of their dammes.</l>
                        <l>At Lammas leaue milking for feare of a thing,</l>
                        <l>leaſt <hi>Requiem eternam</hi> in Winter they ſing.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>94</head>
                        <l>To milke and to folde them, is much to require,</l>
                        <l>except thou haue paſture to fill their deſire.</l>
                        <l>The nightes being ſhort, ſuch hede ye may take,</l>
                        <l>not hurting their bodies, much profite to make.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Fiue ewes to a Cowe milke, go proue by a ſcore,</l>
                        <l>ſhall double thy dairy, elſe truſt me no more.</l>
                        <l>Yet may a good huſwife, that knoweth the ſkill,</l>
                        <l>haue mixt, or vnmixt, at her pleaſure and will.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:20"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>95</head>
                        <l>Gredy of gaine ouer lay not thy ground,</l>
                        <l>and then ſhall thy cattell be luſty and ſounde.</l>
                        <l>But pinch them of paſture, while ſommer doth laſt,</l>
                        <l>and plucke at their tailes, ere and winter be paſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>96</head>
                        <l>To graſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy calues in ſome medow plot nere</l>
                        <l>where neuer their mothers may ſee them nor here:</l>
                        <l>Where water inough is, and barth to fit warme,</l>
                        <l>and looke well vnto them for taking of harme.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>97</head>
                        <l>Pinch wennels at no tyme of water or meate,</l>
                        <l>if euer ye hope for to haue them good neate.</l>
                        <l>In Sommer at all times, in Winter in froſt,</l>
                        <l>if cattell lack drink, they be vtterly loſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ From May to mid Auguſt, from dinner to two,</l>
                        <l>let Patche ſleepe a ſnatch how ſo euer ye do,</l>
                        <l>Though ſleping one hower refreſheth among.</l>
                        <l>yet truſt not Hob grouthed for ſleping to long.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>98</head>
                        <l>In May at the furdeſt twy falow thy land,</l>
                        <l>much drowt may elſe after cauſe plough for to ſtand.</l>
                        <l>This tilth being done, thou haſt paſſed the wurſt,</l>
                        <l>then after who ploweth, plough thou with the furſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>99</head>
                        <l>Get home with thy fewell mede redy to fet,</l>
                        <l>the ſooner, the eaſier, cariage to get.</l>
                        <l>Take hede to thy Bees, that be ready to ſwarme,</l>
                        <l>the loſſe therof now is a crownes worth of harme.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ Iune.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:11778:20"/>
                        <head>100</head>
                        <l>IN Iune get a wedehoke, and a knife &amp; a gloue,</l>
                        <l>&amp; wede out ſuch wedes as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corne doth not loue</l>
                        <l>Slacke neuer thy weding, for dearth nor for cheape,</l>
                        <l>the corne ſhall rewarde it, or euerye reape.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>101</head>
                        <l>The May wede doth burne, &amp; the thiſtle do freat</l>
                        <l>the tyme pulleth downeward the Rie &amp; the Wheat.</l>
                        <l>The Docke and the Brake, noy corne very much,</l>
                        <l>lyke Boddle to Barley, no wede there is ſuch.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>102</head>
                        <l>Waſh ſhepe (for the better) wher water doth ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                        <l>and let them go clenly (and dry) in the Sunne.</l>
                        <l>Then ſhare them &amp; ſpare not, at two dayes an ende,</l>
                        <l>the ſooner, the better, their corps will amende.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>103</head>
                        <l>Rewarde not thy ſhepe when thou takeſt his cote</l>
                        <l>with two or three notches as brode as a grote.</l>
                        <l>Let no ſuch vngentlenes happen to thine,</l>
                        <l>leaſt flye with his gentlenes make it to pine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>104</head>
                        <l>Let lambes go vnclipped til Iune be half worne,</l>
                        <l>the better their coates will be growen to be ſhorne.</l>
                        <l>The Pye will diſcharge the for pulling the reſt,</l>
                        <l>the lighter poore ſheepe is, then fedeth it beſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>105</head>
                        <l>At midſommer down with thy brimbles &amp; brakes</l>
                        <l>and after abrode with thy forkes and thy rakes.</l>
                        <l>Set mowers a work, while y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> medowes be growen,</l>
                        <l>the lenger (now) ſtanding the worſſe to be mowne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>106</head>
                        <l>Prouide of thine owne to haue all thing at hand</l>
                        <l>leaſt worke &amp; the workman, vnwroughten do ſtande.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11778:21"/>
                        <l>Loue ſeldome to borrow, that thinkeſt to ſaue,</l>
                        <l>for he that once lendeth, twiſe looketh to haue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>107</head>
                        <l>Good huſbands that lay to ſaue al thing vpright</l>
                        <l>for tumbrels and cartes haue a ſhed redy dight.</l>
                        <l>A ſtore houſe for trinkets as cloſe as a iayle,</l>
                        <l>that nothing be wanting the worth of a nayle.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>108</head>
                        <l>Thy cartes would be ſearched without &amp; within</l>
                        <l>well clouted and greaſed ere hay time begin.</l>
                        <l>Thy hay being carted, though Carters had ſworne,</l>
                        <l>cartes bottome well boorded, is ſauing of corne.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>¶ Iuly.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>109</head>
                        <l>GO muſter thy ſeruants be captaine thy ſelfe,</l>
                        <l>prouiding them weapon, and other lyke pelfe.</l>
                        <l>Get bottels and wallets, kepe fielde in the heate,</l>
                        <l>the feare is not muche, but the daunger is great.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>110</head>
                        <l>With toſſing and taking and ſetting on cockes,</l>
                        <l>graſſe lately in ſwathes is hay for an Oxe.</l>
                        <l>That done, go and Cart it and haue it away,</l>
                        <l>the battaile is fought, ye haue gotten the day.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>111</head>
                        <l>Let hay be wel made, or auiſe els a vous,</l>
                        <l>for moulding in goef, or for fyering thy houſe.</l>
                        <l>Lay courſeſt aſyde for the Oxe and the Cowe,</l>
                        <l>the fineſt for ſhepe, Calfe and Gelding allowe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>112</head>
                        <l>Then downe with thy hedlondes the corne about</l>
                        <l>leaue neuer a dalop vnmowne and had out.</l>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:11778:21"/>
                        <l>Though graſſe be but thin about barley and peaſe,</l>
                        <l>yet picked vp clene, it ſhal do thee great eaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>113</head>
                        <l>Thy fallow betime for deſtroiyng of weede,</l>
                        <l>leaſt Thiſtle and Dockefall to bloming and ſeede.</l>
                        <l>Such ſeaſon may chance, it ſhall ſtande thee vpon.</l>
                        <l>to till it againe ere the Summer be gon.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>114</head>
                        <l>Thy houſes and barnes would be looked vpon,</l>
                        <l>and al thing amended ere harueſt come on.</l>
                        <l>Things thus ſet in order at quiet and reſt,</l>
                        <l>ſhall furder thy harueſt and pleaſure thee beſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>115</head>
                        <l>Saint Iaimes doth aduiſe to get reapers at had,</l>
                        <l>the corne being ripe doth but ſhed if it ſtand.</l>
                        <l>Be thankfull and ſauing what euer is ſent,</l>
                        <l>God ſendeth the ſame for none other intent.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>116</head>
                        <l>Graunt harueſt Lord more by a peny or two,</l>
                        <l>to call on his felowes the better to do.</l>
                        <l>Giue reapers thy larges, a larges to crye,</l>
                        <l>and alwaies to loyterers haue a good eye.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>117</head>
                        <l>Reape wel, ſcater not gather clene that is ſhorne,</l>
                        <l>binde faſt, ſhock a pace, haue an eye to thy corne.</l>
                        <l>Lode ſafe, carry home, follow time being faire,</l>
                        <l>golfe iuſt in the barne, it is out of diſpaire.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>118</head>
                        <l>In goeuing at harueſt, learne ſkilfully how,</l>
                        <l>eche graine for to lay by it ſelfe on a mow.</l>
                        <l>Sede barley, and peaſon golfe out of the way,</l>
                        <l>all other nygh hand golfe as iuſt as ye may.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:22"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>119</head>
                        <l>Corne caryed, let ſuch as be poore go and cleane,</l>
                        <l>and after let cattel go mouſe it vp cleane.</l>
                        <l>Then ſpare it for paſture till Rowen be paſt</l>
                        <l>to lengthen thy dairy no better thou haſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>120</head>
                        <l>All harueſt time, harueſt folke, ſeruants and all,</l>
                        <l>muſt make altogether good cheare in thy Hall.</l>
                        <l>Go fill them the blacke boll of bleeth to their ſong,</l>
                        <l>and let them be mery all harueſt time long.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>121</head>
                        <l>Once ended thy harueſt let none bee beguilde,</l>
                        <l>pleaſe ſuch as did help thee, man, woman, and childe</l>
                        <l>Thus doing (with alway ſuch helpe as they can)</l>
                        <l>thou winneſt the name of a huſbandly man.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now think vpon God, let thy tong neuer ceaſe,</l>
                        <l>in thanking of him for his mightie encreaſe.</l>
                        <l>Accept my good will, for a proofe go and trye,</l>
                        <l>the better thou thriueſt, the gladder am I.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of all thing this ſeemeth the ſumme, one going, another to come.</head>
                  <l>World laſting looke neuer to lin,</l>
                  <l>yeare ended againe to beginne.</l>
                  <l>Who looketh to wealth to attaine,</l>
                  <l>muſt trauaile againe and againe.</l>
                  <l>Good therefore it is (as I ſay)</l>
                  <l>prouidyng for age, while we may.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:11778:22"/>
                  <head>The kindely propertie of <hi>euery moneth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>11 ¶ Ianuary</head>
                     <l>A kindely good Ianiuere.</l>
                     <l>freaſeth potte by the fier.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>12 ¶ February</head>
                     <l>Fill (Feuerill) dike,</l>
                     <l>with what thou doſt like.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>1 ¶ Marche</head>
                     <l>Marche duſt to be ſolde,</l>
                     <l>woorth raunſomes of golde,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2 ¶ Aprill</head>
                     <l>Swete Aprill ſhowers,</l>
                     <l>do ſpring the May flowers.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3 ¶ May</head>
                     <l>Colde May and a windy,</l>
                     <l>makes Barnes fat and findy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4 ¶ Iune</head>
                     <l>Calme weather in Iune,</l>
                     <l>corne ſetteth in tune.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>5 ¶ Iulye</head>
                     <l>No tempeſt good Iuly,</l>
                     <l>leaſt all things looke ruly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>6 ¶ Auguſt</head>
                     <l>Drye Auguſt and warme,</l>
                     <l>doth harueſt no harme,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>7 ¶ September</head>
                     <l>September blowe ſofte,</l>
                     <l>till fruite be in lofte.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>8 ¶ October</head>
                     <l>October good blaſt,</l>
                     <l>to ſhake the Hog maſt,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>9 ¶ Nouember</head>
                     <l>Nouember take flaile,</l>
                     <l>let ſhip no more ſaile.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>10 ¶ December</head>
                     <l>Oh dirtie December,</l>
                     <l>for Chriſtmas remember.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:23"/>
                  <head>¶ Compairing good huſband with vnthrift his brother, the better deſcerneth the tone from the tother.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>1</head>
                     <l>IL huſbandry braggeth to go with the beſt,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry baggeth vp golde in his cheſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry trudgeth with vnthriftes about,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry ſnudgeth for feare of a dout,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry ſpendeth abrode like a mome,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry tendeth his charges at home.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry ſelleth his corne on the ground,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry ſmelleth no gaine that way found.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>5</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry loſeth for lacke of good fence,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry cloſeth and gaineth the pence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>6</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry truſteth to him and to hir,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry luſteth him ſelfe for to ſtir.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>7</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry eateth him ſelfe out a doore,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry meateth his frind and the poore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>8</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry dayeth or letteth it lie,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry payeth the cheaper to buy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>9</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry lurketh and ſtealeth a ſhepe,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry worketh his houſhold to kepe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>10</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry liueth by that and by this,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry giueth to euery man his.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>11</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry taketh and ſpendeth vp all,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry maketh good ſhift with a ſmall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>12</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry praieth his wife to make ſhift,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry ſayeth take this of my gift.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>13</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry drowſeth at fortune ſo awke,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry rowſeth him ſelfe like a hawke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:11778:23"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>14</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry lieth in pryſon for det,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandrie ſpieth where profit to get.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>25</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry waies hath to fraud what he can,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry praiſe hath of euery man.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>16</head>
                     <l>Ill huſbandry neuer hath welth to kepe touche,</l>
                     <l>good huſbandry euer hath peny in pouche.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="17">
                        <hi>17 <hi>Good huſband his boone or requeſt hath a far,</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ill huſbandry aſſone hath a tode with an R.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>¶ A Sonet where playnelye ye ſee, eche worde to beginne with a T.</head>
                  <l>THe thrifty that teacheth the thriuing to thriue,</l>
                  <l>teach timely to trauerſe the thing that thou triue.</l>
                  <l>Tranſferring thy toyle to the times to thee tought,</l>
                  <l>that teacheth thee te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance to temper thy thought.</l>
                  <l>Think truely to trauaile, that thinkeſt to thee,</l>
                  <l>the trade that the teacher taught truely to thee.</l>
                  <l>Then temper thy trauaile to tary the tide,</l>
                  <l>this teacheth thee thriftineſſe twentie times tride.</l>
                  <l>Take thankfully things, thank tenderly thoſe,</l>
                  <l>that teacheth thee thriftely thy time to tranſpoſe.</l>
                  <l>Troth teached thee two times, teach y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> two times te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                  <l>this trade thou that takeſt, take thrift to thee then.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Tuſſer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Compariſon betvvene</hi> Champion and Seueral.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe countrey encloſed I prayſe,</l>
                     <l>the tother liketh not me.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:24"/>
                     <l>For nothing the welth it doth raiſe,</l>
                     <l>to ſuch as inferior be.</l>
                     <l>Though Champion partly I know,</l>
                     <l>what nede I much thereof to ſhowe?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2</head>
                     <l>There ſwineheard that kepeth the hog,</l>
                     <l>there neathearde with curre and his horne,</l>
                     <l>There ſhepeheard with whiſtle and dog,</l>
                     <l>be fence to the medowes and corne.</l>
                     <l>There horſe beinge tayed on a balke,</l>
                     <l>is ready with theefe for to walke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3</head>
                     <l>Where all thing in common doth reſt.</l>
                     <l>corne fielde with the paſture and mede,</l>
                     <l>Though commen thou doe for the beſt,</l>
                     <l>yet what doth it ſtande thee in ſtede?</l>
                     <l>There commune as communers doe,</l>
                     <l>as good elſe to cobble a ſhoe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4</head>
                     <l>What layer much better than there?</l>
                     <l>or cheaper (thereon to do well)</l>
                     <l>What drudgery more any where,</l>
                     <l>leſſe good thereof where can ye tell?</l>
                     <l>What gotten by Sommer is ſeene,</l>
                     <l>that winter there eateth not cleene.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>5</head>
                     <l>Example by Leiceſter ſhire,</l>
                     <l>what ſoile can be better than that,</l>
                     <l>For any thing hart can deſire.</l>
                     <l>and yet it doth want ye ſe what,</l>
                     <l>Maſt, couert, cloſe paſture, and wood,</l>
                     <l>and other things nedefull as good.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:11778:24"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>6</head>
                     <l>All theſe doth encloſure bring,</l>
                     <l>experience teacheth no leſſe,</l>
                     <l>I ſpeake not to boaſt of the thing.</l>
                     <l>but onely a troth to confeſſe.</l>
                     <l>Example (if doubt ye do make)</l>
                     <l>by Eſſex and Suffolke go take.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>7</head>
                     <l>More plentie of mutton and biefe,</l>
                     <l>corne butter, and cheeſe of the beſt:</l>
                     <l>More wealth anye wheare (to be briefe)</l>
                     <l>more people, more handſome and preſt,</l>
                     <l>Where finde ye? (go ſearch any coaſt)</l>
                     <l>than there where encloſure is moaſte.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>8</head>
                     <l>More worke for the labouring man,</l>
                     <l>as well in the towne as in the fielde,</l>
                     <l>Or thereof (deuiſe if ye can)</l>
                     <l>more profite what countrey do yelde?</l>
                     <l>More ſeldome where ſee ye the poore,</l>
                     <l>go begging from doore vnto doore?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>9</head>
                     <l>More profite is quieter found,</l>
                     <l>(where paſtures in ſeuerall bee)</l>
                     <l>Of one ſiely acre of grounde,</l>
                     <l>than Champion maketh of three.</l>
                     <l>Again what a ioy is it knowen,</l>
                     <l>when men may be bolde of their owne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>10</head>
                     <l>The tone is commended for graine,</l>
                     <l>yet bread made of beanes they do eate:</l>
                     <l>The tother for one loafe haue twaine,</l>
                     <l>of maſtlin, of rye, or of wheate.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:25"/>
                     <l>The Champion liueth full bare,</l>
                     <l>when woodland full mery doth fare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>11</head>
                     <l>Tone geueth his corne in a darth</l>
                     <l>to horſe, ſhepe and hog ery day,</l>
                     <l>The tother giue cattel warme barth,</l>
                     <l>and fede them with ſtrawe and with hay.</l>
                     <l>Corne ſpent of the tone ſo in vaine,</l>
                     <l>the tother doth ſell to his gaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>12</head>
                     <l>Tone barefoote and ragged doth go,</l>
                     <l>and ready in winter to ſterue,</l>
                     <l>When tother ye ſee do not ſo,</l>
                     <l>but hath that is nedefull to ſerue.</l>
                     <l>Tone paine in a cottage do take,</l>
                     <l>when tother trim bowers doth make.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>13</head>
                     <l>Tone layeth for turffe and for ſedge,</l>
                     <l>and hath it with wondefull ſuite,</l>
                     <l>When tother in euery hedge,</l>
                     <l>hath plentie of fewell and fruite.</l>
                     <l>Euils twentie times worſer then theaſe,</l>
                     <l>encloſure full quicklye would eaſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>14</head>
                     <l>In woodland the poore men that haue,</l>
                     <l>ſcarce fully two acres of lande,</l>
                     <l>More merily liue, and do ſaue,</l>
                     <l>than thother with twenty in hand,</l>
                     <l>yet pay they as muche for the two,</l>
                     <l>as tother for twenty muſt do.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:11778:25"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>15</head>
                     <l>The labourer comming from thence,</l>
                     <l>in woodlande to woorke any where.</l>
                     <l>(I warrant you) goeth not hence</l>
                     <l>to worke any more againe there.</l>
                     <l>If this ſame be true (as it is)</l>
                     <l>why gather they nothing of this?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>16</head>
                     <l>The poore at encloſing do grutch,</l>
                     <l>bycauſe of abuſes that fall.</l>
                     <l>Leaſt ſome men ſhould haue but to much,</l>
                     <l>and ſome againe nothing at all.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If order mought therefore be founde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>what were to the ſeuerall grounde.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:26"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:26"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Preface to</hi> the booke of Huſwiferie.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>TAke weapon away, of what force is a man?</l>
                     <l>take huſwife from huſbande &amp; what is he than?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2</head>
                     <l>As louers deſireth together to dwell,</l>
                     <l>ſo huſbandrie loueth good huſwiferie well.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3</head>
                     <l>Though huſbandrie ſemeth to bring in the gaines,</l>
                     <l>yet huſwiferie labours ſeme equall in paynes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4</head>
                     <l>Some reſpite to huſbands the weather doth ſend,</l>
                     <l>but huſwiues affaires haue neuer none ende.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As true as thy faith,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This Huſwiferie ſaith.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I Serue for a day, for a weeke, for a yere,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The praiſe of huſwife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>for lyfe time, for euer, while man dwelleth here.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For richer for porer, from north to the ſouth,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>for honeſt, for hardhed, or daintie of mouth.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For wed, and vnwedded, in ſicknes and health,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>for all that well liueth in good common wealth.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For Citie, for countrey, for Court and for Cart,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>to quiet the head, and to comfort the hart.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:27"/>
                  <head>To the right honorable and my ſpeciall <hi>good Lady and Miſtres, the Lady Paget.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THough payne ſeemeth mickle,</l>
                     <l>and fauour to fickle,</l>
                     <l>yet good will doth tickle</l>
                     <l>my pen for to write,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some knack not vnpretie,</l>
                     <l>of Huſwiferie nettie,</l>
                     <l>how Huſwiues ſhould iettie</l>
                     <l>from morning to night.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not mynding by writing,</l>
                     <l>to ſet them a ſpiting,</l>
                     <l>but ſhewe by endyting,</l>
                     <l>as troth may be bolde:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How huſbandry eaſeth,</l>
                     <l>ſo huſwiferie pleaſeth,</l>
                     <l>and many purſſe greaſeth</l>
                     <l>with ſiluer and golde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bycauſe I did feare me</l>
                     <l>leaſt ſome would forſwere me</l>
                     <l>of trouth I do beare</l>
                     <l>vpright as ye ſee:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Full bent for to loue all</l>
                     <l>and not to reproue all</l>
                     <l>but onely to moue all</l>
                     <l>good Huſwiues to bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For if I ſhould minde ſome</l>
                     <l>or deſcant behinde ſome,</l>
                     <l>and miſſe where to finde ſome,</l>
                     <l>diſpleaſe ſo I mout:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Or if I ſhoudl blend them</l>
                     <l>and ſo to offend them,</l>
                     <l>what talke God ſhould ſend them</l>
                     <l>I ſtand in a dout.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As now if I make this</l>
                     <l>and ſome do well take this,</l>
                     <l>if other forſake this,</l>
                     <l>what profite were that</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Naught elſe but to paine me</l>
                     <l>and nothing to gaine me</l>
                     <l>but make them diſdaine me</l>
                     <l>I wote nere for what.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Leaſt clocke miſſe with dyall,</l>
                     <l>leaſt proufe make deniall,</l>
                     <l>leaſt ſome ſtand to triall,</l>
                     <l>ſome murmure and grudge:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Geue iudgement I pray you</l>
                     <l>(for iuſtly ſo may you)</l>
                     <l>ſo fanſie ſo ſay you,</l>
                     <l>I make you my iudge.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In tyme you ſhal trie me,</l>
                     <l>by trouth you ſhall ſpye me,</l>
                     <l>ſo finde ſo ſet by me</l>
                     <l>according to ſkill:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How euer tree groweth</l>
                     <l>the fruite the tree ſhoweth</l>
                     <l>your Ladyſhip knoweth</l>
                     <l>my heart and good will.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though Fortune doth meaſure,</l>
                     <l>and I do lacke treaſure,</l>
                     <l>yet if I may pleaſure</l>
                     <l>your honour with this:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then wil me to mende it,</l>
                     <l>or mende ere ye ſend it,</l>
                     <l>or any where lende it,</l>
                     <l>if ought be amiſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Ladyſhips ſeruant Thomas Tuſſer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:11778:27"/>
                  <head>¶ A deſcription of Huſwife <hi>and Huſwiferie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>OF huſwife doth Huſwiferie challenge that name,</l>
                     <l>of Huſwiferie Huſwife doth likewiſe the ſame.</l>
                     <l>Where Huſband &amp; Huſbandrie ioyneth with theſe,</l>
                     <l>there wealth being got is preſerued with eaſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The name of a Huſwife, what is it to ſay?</l>
                     <l>the wyfe of the houſe, to the Huſband a ſtay.</l>
                     <l>If huſwife doth that, that belongeth to hir,</l>
                     <l>if Huſband be honeſt there nedeth no ſtir.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Huſwife is ſhee that to labour doth fall,</l>
                     <l>the labour of her I do huſwiferie call.</l>
                     <l>If thrift by that labour be ſaued or got;</l>
                     <l>then is it good huſwiferie, elſe is it not.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The woman the name of a Huſwife doth win,</l>
                     <l>by keping her houſe, and her doings therin.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſhee that with huſband will quietly dwell,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> thinke on this leſſon and follow it well.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Twentie Leſsons alway</hi> to be obſerued.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Serue God is the firſt, 1</head>
                     <l>THe principall point of huſwife in dede,</l>
                     <l>is God to remember the better to ſpede.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ True loue is not worſt. 2</head>
                     <l>A very good leſſon of huſwiferie thought</l>
                     <l>is huſwife with huſband to liue as ſhe ought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ VVife comely no griefe, 3</head>
                     <l>Though trickſie to ſee to, be gallant to wiue,</l>
                     <l>yet comely and wiſe is the huſwife to thriue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Man out huſwife chiefe. 4</head>
                     <l>The huſband abrode, the good wife muſt be chief,</l>
                     <l>and looke to their labour that eateth her biefe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Both out not allowe, 5</head>
                     <l>Where huſband &amp; huſwife be both out of place,</l>
                     <l>there ſeruauntes do loyter and reaſon their caſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Kepe houſe huſwife thou. 6</head>
                     <l>The huſwife ſo named of keping the houſe,</l>
                     <l>muſt tende on her profite as Cat on the Mouſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Seeke home for thy reſt, 7</head>
                     <l>As huſwiues kepe home and be ſtirrers about,</l>
                     <l>ſo ſpeedeth their winninges, the yere throughout.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ For home is the beſt 8</head>
                     <l>Though home be but ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly yet huſwifes are taught</l>
                     <l>that home hath no fellow to ſuch as haue aught.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:28"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Vſe all thing with ſkill 9</head>
                     <l>Good vſage with ſkill, being ſober with all,</l>
                     <l>make huſwiues to ſhine as the ſunne on the wall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ And aſke what ye will. 10</head>
                     <l>What huſband refuſeth things comely to haue,</l>
                     <l>that hath a good wife that will huſwifly ſaue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Be ready at neede, 11</head>
                     <l>The caſe of good huſwiues thus daily doth ſtande</l>
                     <l>what euer ſhall chaunce, to be ready at hand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ That thine is to feede. 12</head>
                     <l>This care hath a huſwife eche hour in her hed,</l>
                     <l>that all thing in time may be huſwifely fed.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ By practiſe go muſe, 13</head>
                     <l>Dame practiſe is ſhe that to huſwife muſt tell,</l>
                     <l>which way for to gouerne her family well.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ How houſholde to vſe. 14</head>
                     <l>Vſe labourers gently, kepe this as a law,</l>
                     <l>make childe for to feare thee, keepe ſeruaunt in awe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Who careleſſe do liue 15</head>
                     <l>Haue euery where a reſpect to thy wayes,</l>
                     <l>that none of thy lyfe any ſlaunder may rayſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Occaſion do giue 16</head>
                     <l>What many do know, though a time it be hid,</l>
                     <l>at length will abrode when a miſchiefe ſhall bid.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ No neighbour reproue 17</head>
                     <l>The loue of thy neighbour ſhall ſtand the in ſteede</l>
                     <l>the poorer the gladder to helpe at a neede.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:29"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ So ſhalt thou haue loue. 18</head>
                     <l>Vſe frendly thy neighbour elſe truſt him in this,</l>
                     <l>as he hath thy frendſhip, ſo truſt vnto his.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Strike nothing vnknowen 19</head>
                     <l>Reuenge not thy wroth vpon any mans beaſt,</l>
                     <l>leaſt thyne by thine enemy come to like feaſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Take heede to thine owne. 20</head>
                     <l>What huſband prouideth with money his drudge,</l>
                     <l>that huſwife muſt looke to, which way it doth trudge</l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>A digreſsion</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>NOw out of the matter this leſſon I had,</l>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Cocke crowing.</note>concerning Cockcrowing, what profit is had.</l>
                        <l>Experience teacheth as true as a clock,</l>
                        <l>how winter nightes paſſeth by marking the Cocke.</l>
                        <l>At midnight one Cocke croweth timely but ſix,</l>
                        <l>with pauſe to his neighbour to aunſwere betwix.</l>
                        <l>At three a clocke thicker, and then as ye knowe,</l>
                        <l>like all in to mattens nere day they do crowe.</l>
                        <l>At midnight, at three, and an houre ere day,</l>
                        <l>Cockes crowe in their language, &amp; thus they do ſay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ If noyſe ye do here</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>looke all thing be clere.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Chant. midnight Anſwere</note>How dame it is midnight, what rubbing is that?</l>
                        <l>take hede to falſe harlots, and more ye wote what.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Both mayden and man</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>mend now what ye can.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:11778:29"/>
                        <l>Maides .iii. a clock, knede,<note place="margin">Chant. Three a clocke.</note> lay your bucks or go brew</l>
                        <l>and cobble and botche ye that can not buy newe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Mayde vp I beſeeche you</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>leaſt Miſtres do breech you.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Anſwere Chant. Toward daye. Anſwere</note>Paſt fiue a clocke holla mayde ſleping beware,</l>
                        <l>leaſt quickly thy dame do vncouer thy bare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Count labour halfe wonne</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>that earely îs done.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Count gaine halfe loſt.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>with watching coſt.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>A hundreth good pointes <hi>of Huſwiferye.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ No ſoner Sunne vp.</head>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">morning.</note>GEt vp in the morning as ſoone as thou wilt,</l>
                        <l>with ouer long ſlugging good ſeruant is ſpilt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ But noſe in the cup. 2</head>
                        <l>Some ſlouens from ſleping no ſooner be vp,</l>
                        <l>but hand is in Aumberie, and noſe in the cup.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ That earely is done. 3</head>
                        <l>Some works in the morning may trimly be done,</l>
                        <l>that al the day after can neuer be wonne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Count huſwifely wonne. 4</head>
                        <l>Good huſband without maketh welthy and fat,</l>
                        <l>good huſwife within is as nedefull as that.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Caſt duſt in the yarde. 5</head>
                        <l>Sluttes corners auoided, ſhal farther thy health,</l>
                        <l>much time about trifles ſhal hinder thy wealth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:30"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Go ſpin and go carde. 6</head>
                        <l>Set ſome about charning, ſome ſeething of ſouſe,</l>
                        <l>ſome carding, ſome ſpinning, ſom trimming vp houſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Do as ye ſhall thinke. 7</head>
                        <l>Set ſome to grinde mault, or thy ruſſhes to twine,</l>
                        <l>ſet ſome to peele hempe, or to ſeething of brine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Let meat neuer ſtinke. 8</head>
                        <l>Some corneth, ſom brineth, ſom wil not be taught</l>
                        <l>wher meat taketh vent, there the huſwife is naught.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To breakfaſt that come.</head>
                        <l n="9">
                           <note place="margin">Brekfaſt</note> 
                           <hi>9</hi> Call ſeruants to breakfaſt by day ſtarre appere,</l>
                        <l>a ſnatch and to worke fellowes, tarry not here.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Geue euery one ſome. 10</head>
                        <l>Let huſwife be caruer, let pottage be eate,</l>
                        <l>a diſhfull eche one with a morſell of meate.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ No more tittle tattle. 11</head>
                        <l>What tacke in a pudding ſayth gredy gut wringer</l>
                        <l>giue ſuch ye wote what, ere pudding they finger.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To ſeruing your cattle.</head>
                        <l n="12">
                           <note place="margin">Fore no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e workes.</note> 
                           <hi>12</hi> Let ſeruants once ſerued, thy cattle go ſerue,</l>
                        <l>elſe maiſter and miſtreſſe may quickly go ſterue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Learne you that will thee. 13</head>
                        <l>No breakfaſt of cuſtome prouide not to ſaue,</l>
                        <l>but onely to ſuch as deſerueth to haue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Some daintie wil bee. 14</head>
                        <l>No ſhewing to ſeruant what vitailes in ſtore,</l>
                        <l>ſhew ſeruants their labour and ſhew them no more.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:11778:30"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Of hauock beware. 15</head>
                        <l>Where al things is common, what nedeth a hutch?</l>
                        <l>where wanteth a ſauer, there hauock is much.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Falſe Cattes will not ſpare. 16</head>
                        <l>Where windows ſtand open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cattes make a fray</l>
                        <l>yet wilde cats with two legs are worſer then they.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Looke well vnto thine. 17</head>
                        <l>An eye in a corner who vſeth to haue,</l>
                        <l>reueleth a drab, and preuenteth a knaue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Slut ſlouthfull muſt whine. 18</head>
                        <l>Make maide to be clenly, or make her crye creake,</l>
                        <l>&amp; teach her to ſtirre when her miſtreſſe doth ſpeake.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Let holly wand threat. 19</head>
                        <l>A wand in thy hand though ye fight not all,</l>
                        <l>make youth to their buſineſſe the better to fall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Let fiſgig be beat. 20</head>
                        <l>For feare of a foole had I wiſt cauſe thee to waile</l>
                        <l>let fiſgig be taught to ſhut dore after tayle.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To eaſy the wicket. 21</head>
                        <l>With hir that will clicket, make daunger to cope,</l>
                        <l>leaſt happily hir wicket be eaſy to ope.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Will ſtill appeaſe clicket. 22</head>
                        <l>As rod lytell mendeth where maners be ſpilt,</l>
                        <l>ſo naught wilbe nought ſay and do what thou wilt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Fight ſeldome ye ſhall. 23</head>
                        <l>Much brauling with ſeruants what man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abide</l>
                        <l>pay home when thou fighteſt but loue not to chide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:31"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Loue neuer to brall. 24</head>
                        <l>As order is heauenly where quiet is had,</l>
                        <l>ſo errour is hel, or a miſchief as bad.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ What better lawe. 25</head>
                        <l>Such law as a warning will cauſe to beware,</l>
                        <l>doth make the whole houſe the better to fare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To ſeruants than awe. 26</head>
                        <l>The leſſe of thy councell thy ſeruants doth know</l>
                        <l>their duetie the better ſuch ſeruants ſhall ſhowe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Good muſicke regarde. 27</head>
                        <l>Such ſeruants are often both paineful and good</l>
                        <l>that ſing in their labours as birdes in the wood.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Good ſeruaunts rewarde 28</head>
                        <l>Good ſeruants hope iuſtly ſome frendſhip to fele,</l>
                        <l>and looke to haue fauour what time they do wele.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ By one time or twiſe. 29</head>
                        <l>Take runnagate Robbins to pittie their nede,</l>
                        <l>and looke to be filched as true as thy Creede.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Is good to be wiſe. 30</head>
                        <l>Take warning by once, that a worſe do not hap,</l>
                        <l>foreſight is the ſtopper of many a gap.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Some chaunge for a ſhift. 31</head>
                        <l>Make fewe of thy councell to change for the beſt,</l>
                        <l>leaſt one that is trudging in fetcheth the reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Much chaunge little thrift. 32</head>
                        <l>The ſtone that is rolling can gather no Moſſe,</l>
                        <l>for Maiſtres and maydes, by oft changing is loſſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:11778:31"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Both liberal ſticketh. 33</head>
                        <l>One Dog for a Hogge, and one Cat for a Mouſe,</l>
                        <l>one ready to giue is inough in a houſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Some prouender pricketh. 34</head>
                        <l>One gift ill accepted, kepe next in thy purſe,</l>
                        <l>whom prouender pricketh are often the wurſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Brewe ſomewhat for thine. 35</head>
                        <l>Where brewer is nedefull be brewer thy ſelfe,</l>
                        <l>what filleth the roofe, wil helpe furniſh thy ſhelfe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Elſe bring vp no Swine. 36</head>
                        <l>In buying thy drink by the firkin or Pot,</l>
                        <l>the ſkore doth ariſe, the Hogge profiteth not.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Well brewed worth coſt. 37</head>
                        <l>One buſſhell wel brewed, out laſteth ſome twaine</l>
                        <l>two troubles for one thing is coſt to no gaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Ill vſed halfe loſt. 38</head>
                        <l>To new is no profit, to ſtale is as bad,</l>
                        <l>drinke ſower or dead maketh huſband halfe mad.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Remember good Gill. 39</head>
                        <l>Put graines to more water while graines be yet hot,</l>
                        <l>&amp; ſeeth them &amp; ſturre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as otemeale in pot.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Take payne with thy ſwill. 40</head>
                        <l>Though heating be coſtly, ſuch ſwil yet in ſtore,</l>
                        <l>ſhall profit thy porkelings a hundreth times more.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ New bred is the Diuell. 41</head>
                        <l>Newe bread is a waſter, but mouldy is wurſe,</l>
                        <l>what Dogge getteth that way that loſeth the purſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:32"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Much cruſt is as euill. 42</head>
                        <l>Much dowebake I praiſe not, much cruſt is as ill</l>
                        <l>the meane is the huſwife, ſay nay if ye wil.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Good daîry doth eaſe. 43</head>
                        <l>Good ſeruant in dairye that nedes not be tolde,</l>
                        <l>deſerueth hir fee to be paide hir in golde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Good cokerye doth pleaſe. 44</head>
                        <l>Good Cooke to dreſſe dinner, to bake &amp; to brewe,</l>
                        <l>is better than golde being honeſt and true.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Good droye yong or olde. 45</head>
                        <l>Good droy to ſerue hogs, to help waſh &amp; to milke,</l>
                        <l>is ſome time as nedefull as ſome in their ſilke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Good whitemeat worthe golde. 46</head>
                        <l>Kepe dayrie houſe clenly, kepe pan ſwete and told</l>
                        <l>kepe butter and cheeſe to looke yellow as golde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Make clenly thy guttes. 47</head>
                        <l>Saue charmmilke, ſaue welcord, ſaue puddig and ſouſe,</l>
                        <l>ſuch offall doth ſtop many gappes in a houſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ And learne to know ſluttes. 48</head>
                        <l>Though homely be milker, let clenly be Cooke,</l>
                        <l>for dropnoſe and ſlut may be knowen by their looke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ In dairy no Cat. 49</head>
                        <l>Though Cat being good is a iewel in houſe,</l>
                        <l>yet euer in dairy haue trappe for a mouſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Lay bane for a Rat. 50</head>
                        <l>Take hede how thou layeſt the bane for the rats,</l>
                        <l>for poyſoning ſeruants, thy ſelfe and thy brattes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:11778:32"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ No ſcouring for pride. 51</head>
                        <l>Though ſcouring be nedefull, yet ſcourig to mutch</l>
                        <l>is pride without profite, and robbeth thine hutch.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Kepe kettle whole ſide, 52</head>
                        <l>Kepe kettles from knocks, &amp; ſet tubs out of ſunne,</l>
                        <l>for mending is coſtly, and crackt is ſoone done.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Take hede when ye waſh. 53</head>
                        <l>Maides waſh wel &amp; wring well, but beat ye wot how.</l>
                        <l>if any lacke beating, I feare it be you.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Els runne in the laſh. 54</head>
                        <l>In waſhing by hand, haue an eye to thy boll,</l>
                        <l>for Launders and millers be quicke of their toll.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Drye Sunne or drye wynde. 55</head>
                        <l>Go waſh wel ſaieth Somer, with ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne I ſhal dry,</l>
                        <l>go wring well ſaith winter, with winde ſo ſhal I.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Safe binde and ſafe finde. 56</head>
                        <l>To truſt without hede is to venter a ioynt,</l>
                        <l>giue tale and take count is a huſwifely point.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Where none fall a packing. 57</head>
                        <l>When he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes fall a cackling, take hede to their neſt</l>
                        <l>when drabbes fall a whiſtring take hede to the reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ There nothing is lacking. 58</head>
                        <l>What Huſband refuſeth things comely to haue,</l>
                        <l>that hath a good wife that wil huſwifely ſane.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Yll made better left. 59</head>
                        <l>The place may be ſo, &amp; the Kill may be ſuch,</l>
                        <l>to make thine owne Mault, ſhall profit chee much.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:33"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Wood dried hath a weſt. 60</head>
                        <l>Som drieth with ſtraw, &amp; ſom drieth with wood</l>
                        <l>wood aſketh more charge, &amp; yet nothing ſo good.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Let Mault be made well. 61</head>
                        <l>Mault being wel ſpered the more it wil coſt,</l>
                        <l>mault being wel dryed the longer will laſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Take hede to thy kell. 62</head>
                        <l>Let Gillet be ſinging, it doth very well,</l>
                        <l>to kepe hir from ſleping and burning the kell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ For hunger or thirſt. 63</head>
                        <l>By noone let your dinner be ready and neate,</l>
                        <l>let meat tarry ſeruant not ſeruant his meat.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Dreſſe cattel well firſt. 64</head>
                        <l>The plough teme a bayting,<note place="margin">Dinner.</note> cal ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to dinner,</l>
                        <l>the thicker, ſo much be the charges the thinner.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Together is beſt. 65</head>
                        <l>Dewe ſeaſon is beſt, altogether is gay,</l>
                        <l>diſpatch hath no fellow, make ſhort and away.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ For hoſtis and geſt. 66</head>
                        <l>Beware of Gill laggoſe diſordering thy houſe,</l>
                        <l>more dainties who catcheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> craftie fed Mouſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Let ſuch haue inough. 67</head>
                        <l>Giue ſeruants no dainties, but giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inough,</l>
                        <l>to many chappes walking doth begger the plough.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ That follow the plough. 68</head>
                        <l>Poore ſeggons halfe ſterued work faintly &amp; dull,</l>
                        <l>and lubbers do loyter, their bellies to full.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:11778:33"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Geue neuer to much, 69</head>
                        <l>Feede lazie that threſheth a flap and a tap,</l>
                        <l>lyke ſlouthfull that all day be ſtopping a gap.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To lubbers and ſuch. 70</head>
                        <l>Some houſholdly lubber more eateth then twoe,</l>
                        <l>yet leaueth vndone that a ſtranger will doe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Spare ſuch as thou haſt, 71</head>
                        <l>Some cutteth thy linnen, ſome ſpilleth their broth</l>
                        <l>bare table to ſuche doth as well as a cloth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Where nothing will laſt. 72</head>
                        <l>Trene diſhes doth wel, wodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpones go to wrack</l>
                        <l>where ſtone is no laſter, take tankarde and iacke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Knap boy on the thumbes, 73</head>
                        <l>That pewter is neuer for manerly feaſt,</l>
                        <l>that dayly doth ſerue an vninanerly beaſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ And ſaue him his crummes. 74</head>
                        <l>Some gnaweth &amp; leueth ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e cruſts &amp; ſome crums,</l>
                        <l>eat ſuch their own leauigs, or gnaw their own thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bs</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Serue God euer furſt, 75</head>
                        <l>At Dinner, at Supper, at Morning at Night,</l>
                        <l>Giue thankes vnto god for his giftes in thy ſight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Take nothing at wurſt. 76</head>
                        <l>Good huſband and huſwife will ſome tune alone,</l>
                        <l>dyne well with a morſell and ſuppe with a bone.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Enough thou art tolde, 77</head>
                        <l>Three diſhes well dreſſed, and welcome withall,</l>
                        <l>both pleaſeth thy frende and becommeth thine Hall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:34"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To much will not holde. 78</head>
                        <l>Enough is a plentie, to much is a pride,</l>
                        <l>vnſkilfull the holder, plough goeth aſyde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <note place="margin">After none workes.</note>¶ Make company breake, 79</head>
                        <l>When Dinner is ended ſet ſeruaunts to woorke,</l>
                        <l>and follow ſuch Marchants as loueth to lurke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Go cheriſhe the weake. 80</head>
                        <l>To ſeruant in ſickneſſe ſee nothing ye grutch.</l>
                        <l>a thing of a trifle ſhall comfort him mutch.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ who many do feede, 81</head>
                        <l>Put chipping in dippings, vſe parings to ſaue,</l>
                        <l>fatt Capons or Hennes ye that looke for to haue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Saue much thei had neede. 82</head>
                        <l>Saue drippings and ſkimmings how euer ye do,</l>
                        <l>for medicine, for cattle, for Carte, and for ſhoo.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Leaue Capon vnmeete, 83</head>
                        <l>All of corne thy pulleine muſt haue for their fee,</l>
                        <l>feede willingly ſuch as do helpe to feede thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Fatt coſtly vnſweete. 84</head>
                        <l>Though fat fed be daintie, of this I the warne,</l>
                        <l>be cunning in fatting for robbing thy barne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Peece hole to defende, 85</head>
                        <l>Good ſemeſters be ſowing of fine pretie knackes,</l>
                        <l>good huſwiues be mending and peecing their ſackes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Thinges tymely amende. 86</head>
                        <l>Though making &amp; mending be huſwifely wayes,</l>
                        <l>yet mending in tyme is the huſwife to prayſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:11778:34"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Buy newe as ye may. 87</head>
                        <l>Though Ladyes may rend and by new ery day,</l>
                        <l>good huſwifes muſt mende &amp; by newe as they may.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Loſe nothing I ſay. 88</head>
                        <l>Cal quarterly ſeruants to court and to lete,</l>
                        <l>write euery Couerlet, Blanket and Shete.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Shift ſlouenly elfe, 89</head>
                        <l>Though ſhifting to oft be a theefe in a houſe,</l>
                        <l>yet ſhift goodman ſlouen for feare of a louſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Be Gaoler thy ſelfe. 90</head>
                        <l>Graunt doubtfull no keye of his cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in purſſe,</l>
                        <l>leaſt Chamber dore locke be to thiefrie a Nurſſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Saue feathers for geſt, 91</head>
                        <l>Saue wing for threſher when Gander doth dye,</l>
                        <l>ſaue feathers of all thing the ſofter to lye.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Theſe foure rob cheſt. 92</head>
                        <l>Much ſpice is a thiefe, ſo is candle and fier,</l>
                        <l>ſwete ſauſe is as craftie as euer was Frier.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ wife make thine owne candle, 93</head>
                        <l>Prouide for thy tallow ere froſt commeth in,</l>
                        <l>and make thine owne Candle ere winter begin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Leaue peny to handle. 94</head>
                        <l>If peny for all thing be ſuffred to trudge,</l>
                        <l>truſt long not to peny, to haue him thy drudge.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Tyme drawing to night, 95</head>
                        <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes go to houſe, ſet thy cooke to dreſſe meat</l>
                        <l>ſome milke, &amp; ſerue hogs, and ſet ſome to ſerue neat.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:35"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ See all thinges go right. 96</head>
                        <l>Where twaine be inough, be not ſerued with three</l>
                        <l>more knaues in a company worſer they be.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Make Lackie to trudge, 97</head>
                        <l>For euery trifle leaue iauncing thy Nagge,</l>
                        <l>but rather make Lacky of Iack boy thy Nagge.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Make ſeruant thy drudge. 98</head>
                        <l>Make ſeruant at night, lug in wood or a Log.</l>
                        <l>let none come in emptie but ſlutte and thy Dog.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Falſe knaue ready preſt, 99</head>
                        <l>Where pulleine vſe nightly to pearch in the yarde,</l>
                        <l>there two legged Foxes keepe watches and warde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ All well is the beſt. 100</head>
                        <l>See cattell well ſerued without and within,</l>
                        <l>and all thing at quiet ere Supper begin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Take heede it is needefull, 101</head>
                        <l>No clothes in garden,<note place="margin">Euening woorkes</note> no trinkets without,</l>
                        <l>no doore left vnbolted for feare of a doubt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ True pitie is meedefull. 102</head>
                        <l>Thou woman whome pitie becometh the beſt,</l>
                        <l>graunt all that hath laboured, tyme to take reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Vſe mirth and good woorde,</head>
                        <l n="103">
                           <note place="margin">Supper</note> 
                           <hi>103</hi> Prouide for thy huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to make him good chere,</l>
                        <l>make mery together while tyme ye be here.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ At bed and at boorde. 104</head>
                        <l>At bed and at borde how ſo euer be fall,</l>
                        <l>what euer God ſendeth be mery withall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:11778:35"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ No ſkirmiſhing make 105</head>
                        <l>No taunts before ſeruants for hindring thy fame</l>
                        <l>no iarring to loude for auoiding of ſhame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>No ielouſie take. 106</head>
                        <l>As franſie and hereſie roueth together,</l>
                        <l>ſo ielouſie leadeth a foole ye wote whether.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Rewarde as ye haue, 107</head>
                        <l>Yong children &amp; chickens would euer be eating,</l>
                        <l>good ſeruauntes looke duely for gentle entreating.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ No talkatiue knaue, 108</head>
                        <l>No ſeruaunt at table vſe ſauſly to talke,</l>
                        <l>leaſt tongue ſet at large out of meaſure do walke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ No ſnatching at all, 109</head>
                        <l>No lurching, no ſnatching, nor ſtriuing at all,</l>
                        <l>leaſt one go without and another haue all.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Sirs harken now all, 110</head>
                        <l>Declare after Supper, take hede thereunto,<note place="margin">Woorkes after ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>what worke in the morning eche ſeruant ſhal do.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Thy ſoule hath a clog, 111</head>
                        <l>Remember thoſe children whoſe pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts be poore,</l>
                        <l>which hunger, yet dare not to craue at thy doore.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Forget not thy Dog. 112</head>
                        <l>Thy bandog that ſerueth for dyucrs miſhappes,</l>
                        <l>forget not to geue him thy bones and thy ſcrappes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Make keyes to be kepers, 113</head>
                        <l>Where mouthes be many to ſpend that thou haſt</l>
                        <l>ſet keyes to be kepers for ſpending to faſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11778:36"/>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To bed drouſie ſlepers. 114</head>
                        <l>To bed after ſupper, let drouſie go ſlepe,</l>
                        <l>leaſt knaue in the darke to his marrow do creepe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Kepe keyes as thy life, 115</head>
                        <l>Such keyes lay vp ſafe ere ye take ye to reſt,</l>
                        <l>of dairy, of Buttery of Cuphorde and Cheſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Feare candle good wife. 116</head>
                        <l>Feare candle in hay loft in Barne and in Shed,</l>
                        <l>feare flea ſmock, &amp; mendbreech, for burning their bed.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Night workes trouble hed, 117</head>
                        <l>The day willeth done what ſo euer ye bid,</l>
                        <l>the night is a theefe if ye take not good heede,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ Locke doores and to bed. 118</head>
                        <l>Waſhe diſhes, lay leauens, ſafe fyer and away,</l>
                        <l>locke doores and to bed a good huſwife will ſay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To bed know thy guiſe, 119</head>
                        <l>In winter at nyne; and in Sommer at tenne,</l>
                        <l>to bed after Supper both maydens and menne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>¶ To riſe do likewiſe. 120</head>
                        <l>In winter at fiue a clocke ſeruant aryſe,</l>
                        <l>in Sommer at foure is euer the guyſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>¶ Liue well and long.</l>
                        <l>forbeare now among.</l>
                        <l>Be lowly not ſolen if ought go amiſſe,</l>
                        <l>what wreſting may loſe thee, that winne with a kiſſe,</l>
                        <l>Both heare and forbeare now and then as ye may,</l>
                        <l>then Wenche God a mercy thy huſband will ſaye.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:11778:36"/>
                  <head>The plough mans feaſting times.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This would not be ſlept,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>olde guiſe muſt be kept.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>GOod Huſwiues whom God hath enriched enough<note place="margin">Feaſting dayes</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>forget not the feaſtes that belong to the Plough,</l>
                     <l>The meaning is onely to ioy and be glad,</l>
                     <l>for comfort with labour would ſometune be had.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Plough Monday.</head>
                     <l>Plough Monday, the next after Twelftide be paſt,<note place="margin">At twelfe tyde</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>biddeth out with the plough, the worſt huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is laſt.</l>
                     <l>If Ploughman get hatchet or whip to the ſcrene,</l>
                     <l>maydes loſeth their Cocke if no water be ſeene.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Shroftide.</head>
                     <l>At ſhroftide to ſhrouing, go threſh the fatte henne,<note place="margin">At ſhroftid</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>if blindfilde can kill it then giue it thy menne.</l>
                     <l>Maydes fritters and Pancakes inough ſee ye make,</l>
                     <l>let ſlutte haue one pancake for company ſake.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Sheepe ſhering.</head>
                     <l>Wyfe make vs a feaſt, ſpare fleſhe neyther corne,<note place="margin">At midſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>make Wafers &amp; Cakes, for our ſhepe muſt be ſhorne,</l>
                     <l>At ſhepe ſhering neighbours no other thing craue,</l>
                     <l>but good chere &amp; welcome, like neighbours to haue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ The wake day.</head>
                     <l>To Ouen with the flawnes mayd, paſſe not for ſlepe,<note place="margin">Wake day.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>to morow thy father his wake day ſhal kepe:</l>
                     <l>Then trimly go daunce with what Louer ye will,</l>
                     <l>though loue make you beaten, kepe Louer yet ſtill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:37"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Harueſt home.</head>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">In Auguſt.</note>For all this good feaſting yet art thou not looſe,</l>
                     <l>till thou giue the Ploughman in harueſt his gooſe.</l>
                     <l>Though gooſe go in ſtubble, yet paſſe not for that</l>
                     <l>let gooſe haue a gooſe be ſhee leane be ſhee fat.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Seede Cake.</head>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">At Hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe.</note>Wife ſome time this weeke if that all thing go cleare,</l>
                     <l>an ende of wheat ſowing we make for this yeare.</l>
                     <l>Remember you therefore, though I do it not,</l>
                     <l>the Seede Cake, the Paſties, and Furmentie pot.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>¶ Twiſe a weke roſt.</head>
                     <l>Good Ploughmen looke wekely of cuſtome &amp; right,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Twiſe a weke roſt.</note>for roſtmeat on Sondayes &amp; Thurſdaies at night.</l>
                     <l>Thus doing and keping ſuch cuſtome and guiſe,</l>
                     <l>they call thee good huſwife, they loue thee likewiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The good huſwifely <hi>Phiſicke.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>GOod huſwiues prouide ere an ſicknes doth come,</l>
                  <l>of ſundry good thinges in her houſe to haue ſome.</l>
                  <l>Good <hi>Aqua compoſita,</hi> Vineger tart,</l>
                  <l>Roſe water and Treacle to comfort the hart,</l>
                  <l>Colde herbes in her Garden for Agues that burne,</l>
                  <l>that ouer ſtrong heate to good temper may turne.</l>
                  <l>With Endiue and Suckery, with Spinage ynough,</l>
                  <l>all ſuch with good pot herbes ſhould follow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plough.</l>
                  <l>Get water of Fumetory, Lyuer to coole,</l>
                  <l>and others the like, or els go like a foole.</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:11778:37"/>
                  <l>Conſerue of Barbery, Quinces and ſuch,</l>
                  <l>with Sirops that eaſeth the ſickly ſo much.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Phiſition</note>Aſk Medicus councel ere medicine ye make,</l>
                  <l>and honour that man for neceſſities ſake.</l>
                  <l>Though thouſands hate Phiſicke becauſe of the coſt</l>
                  <l>yet thouſands it helpeth that elſe ſhould be loſt.</l>
                  <l>Good broth &amp; good keeping doth much now &amp; than,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">good diet</note>good diet with wiſedome beſt helpeth a man.</l>
                  <l>In health to be ſturring ſhall profite thee beſt,</l>
                  <l>in ſickeneſſe hate trouble, ſeeke quiet and reſt.</l>
                  <l>Remember thy ſoule,<note place="margin">Think on thy ſoule Haue a good hart</note> let no fanſie preuaile,</l>
                  <l>make ready to Godward let hart neuer quaile.</l>
                  <l>The ſooner thy ſelfe thou ſubmitteſt to God,</l>
                  <l>the ſooner he ceaſeth to ſcourge with his rod.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The good motherly <hi>Nuſſerie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Good huſwiues take paine,<note place="margin">Mother beſt nurſe</note> &amp; do count it good luck,</l>
                  <l>to make their own breſts their own child to giue ſuck</l>
                  <l>Though wrauling and rocking be noyſome ſo neare,</l>
                  <l>yet loſt by ill nurſing is worſer to heare.</l>
                  <l>But one thing I warne thee, let huſwife be nurſſe,</l>
                  <l>leaſt huſband doth find thee to frank with his purſe.</l>
                  <l>What hilbacke and fill belly maketh away,</l>
                  <l>that helpe to make good,<note place="margin">Hilbak &amp; fil belly Big and the twig.</note> or elſe looke for a fray.</l>
                  <l>Giue childe that is fitly giue baby the bigge,</l>
                  <l>giue hardeneſſe to youth and giue coperipe a twigge</l>
                  <l>We finde it not ſpoken ſo often for naught,</l>
                  <l>that children were better vnborne than vntaught.</l>
                  <l>Some Cockneis with cocking are made very fooles</l>
                  <l>fit neither for Prentice, for plough nor for ſchooles.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11778:38"/>
                  <l>Teach childe to aſke bleſſing,<note place="margin">ſerue god</note> ſerue God &amp; to church,</l>
                  <l>then bleſſe as a mother: elſe bleſſe him with burch.</l>
                  <l>Thou huſwife thus doing what further ſhall nede,</l>
                  <l>but all men to call thee good huſwife in dede.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Thinke on the poore.</head>
                  <l>REmember the poore, that for Gods ſake do call,</l>
                  <l>for God both rewardeth and bleſſeth with all.</l>
                  <l>Take this in good part, what ſo euer thou bee,</l>
                  <l>and wiſhe me no worſe than I wiſhe vnto thee.</l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="part">
            <head>For men a perfect warning, what childe ſhall come by learning.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ALl you that faine would learne a perfect way,</l>
               <l>to haue your children in muſick ſome thing ſene:</l>
               <l>Aſke nature firſt what thereto ſhe doth ſay,</l>
               <l>ere further ſute ye make to ſuch a Queene.</l>
               <l>For doubtleſſe <hi>Croſſum Gaput</hi> is not he,</l>
               <l>of whom the learned Muſes ſeene will bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once tryed that nature trim hath done her part,</l>
               <l>and Lady Muſicke farre in loue withall:</l>
               <l>Be wiſe who firſt doth teach thy childe that art,</l>
               <l>leaſt homely breaker marre fine ambling ball.</l>
               <l>Not rod in madbraines hand is that can helpe,</l>
               <l>but gentle ſkill doth make the proper whelpe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:11778:38"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Wheare choiſe is harde, count good for well a fine,</l>
               <l>ſkill mixt with will, is he that teacheth beſt:</l>
               <l>Let this ſuffiſe for teaching childe of thine,</l>
               <l>chuſe quickly well for all thy lingering reſt.</l>
               <l>Miſtaught at firſt howe ſeldome proueth well?</l>
               <l>trim taught (O God) how ſhortly doth excell?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although as ſhippes muſt tarry winde and tyde,</l>
               <l>and perfect houres abide their ſtinted time:</l>
               <l>So likewiſe, though of learning (daily tride)</l>
               <l>ſpace muſt be had ere wit may thereto clime:</l>
               <l>Yet eaſie ſteppes, and perfect way to truſt,</l>
               <l>doth cauſe good ſpeede, confeſſe of force we muſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus in the childe though wit inough we finde,</l>
               <l>and teacher good neare hand, or other where:</l>
               <l>And time as apt as may be thought with minde,</l>
               <l>nor cauſe in ſuch thing much to doubt or feare:</l>
               <l>Yet cocking Mams, &amp; ſhifting Dads from ſchooles,</l>
               <l>make pregnant wittes to proue vnlearned fooles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ere learning come, to haue firſt art thou taught,</l>
               <l>apt learning childe, apt time that think to frame,</l>
               <l>Apt cunning man to teach, elſe all is naught.</l>
               <l>apt parents glad to bring to paſſe the ſame.</l>
               <l>On ſuch apt ground the Muſes loue to builde,</l>
               <l>this leſſon learne: adewe elſe learned childe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11778:39"/>
            <head>A ſonet to the Lady Paget.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SOme pleaſures take, and can not giue,</l>
               <l>but onely make poore thanks their ſhift:</l>
               <l>Some meaning well in det do liue,</l>
               <l>nor cannot tell how els to ſhift.</l>
               <l>Some knocke and faine would ope the doore,</l>
               <l>to learne the vaine good turne to praiſe:</l>
               <l>Some ſhew good face, and be but poore,</l>
               <l>yet haue a grace good fame to rayſe.</l>
               <l>Some owe and giue, yet ſtill in det,</l>
               <l>and ſo muſt liue for ought I knowe:</l>
               <l>Some wiſhe to pay and cannot get,</l>
               <l>but night and day ſtill more do owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Euen ſo muſt I for pleaſures paſt,</l>
               <l>ſtill wiſhe you good while life doth laſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A Compariſon betvvene good <hi>Huſwifery and euill.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>Comparing together good huſwife and bad,</l>
               <l>The knowledge of either the better is had.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>1</head>
               <l>IL huſwiferie lieth till nine of the clocke,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie tryeth to riſe with the Cocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie tooteth to make her ſelfe braue,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie looketh what houſholde muſt haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie truſteth to him and to her,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie luſteth her ſelfe for to ſtir.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie cares not for this nor for that.</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie ſpareth for feare ye wote what.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:11778:39"/>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferye pricketh her ſelfe vp in pride,</l>
               <l>good huſwifery tricketh her houſe as a bride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>Ill huſwifery o thinge or other muſte craue,</l>
               <l>good huſwifery nothing but nedefull will haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7</head>
               <l>Ill huſwifery moueth with goſſeps to ſpend,</l>
               <l>good huſwifery loueth her houſholde to tende.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8</head>
               <l>Ill huſwifery wanteth with ſpending to faſt,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferye ſcanteth, the lenger to laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>9</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferye eaſeth her ſelfe with vnknowne,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferye pleaſeth her ſelfe with her owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>10</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie brooketh mad toies in her hed,</l>
               <l>good huſwifery looketh that al things be fed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>11</head>
               <l>Ill huſwifery bringeth a ſhilling to naught,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie ſingeth, her cofers all fraught.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>12</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie renteth and caſteth a ſide,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie mendeth, elſe would it go wide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>13</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie ſwepeth her linnen to gage,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie kepeth to ſerue her in age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>14</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie craueth in ſecret to borrowe,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie ſaueth to day for to morrowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>15</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie pineth (not hauing to eate)</l>
               <l>good huſwifrie dineth with plentie of meate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>16</head>
               <l>Ill huſwiferie letteth the Diuell to take all,</l>
               <l>good huſwiferie ſetteth good brag of a ſmall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>17</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>17 Good huſwife good fame hath of beſt in the towne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>yll huſwife yll name hath of euery Clowne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11778:40"/>
            <head>Huſbandly poſies for the hall.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>1</head>
               <l>FRend here I dwell, and here I haue a little wordly pelfe:</l>
               <l>which on my friend I kepe to ſpende, as well as on my ſelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>What euer fare thou hap to finde, take welcome for the beſt:</l>
               <l>that hauing then, diſdaine thou not, for wanting of the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>Bachyting talke, the flattering blabs, knowe wily how to ble<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge,</l>
               <l>the wiſe doth note, the frende doth hate, the enmie will reuenge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>The wiſe wil ſpende, or geue &amp; lend, yet kepe or haue in ſtore:</l>
               <l>if fooles may haue from hand to mouth, they pas vppon no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>Where eaſe is ſought, at length we ſee, that plenty waxeth ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</l>
               <l>who careleſſe liue, go borrow muſt, or elſe, full often want.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>The world doth think the welthy man is he that leaſt ſhall nede</l>
               <l>but God doth know the vertuous man is he that beſt ſhal ſpede.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Poſies for the parler.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>1</head>
               <l>AS hatred is the ſerpents noyſome rod,</l>
               <l>ſo frendſhip is the louing gifte of God.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>The dronken frende is frendſhip very euill,</l>
               <l>the frantike frend, is frendſhip for the Deuill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>The quiet frend all one in word and dede,</l>
               <l>great comfort is like redy golde at neede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>With brauling fooles, that wrall for euery wrong,</l>
               <l>firme frendſhip neuer can continue long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>In time that man ſhall ſeldome frendſhip miſſe,</l>
               <l>that wayeth what thing, touch kept in frendſhip is.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>Oft times a frend is got with eaſte coſt,</l>
               <l>which vſed euill, is oft as quickly loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:11778:40"/>
            <lg>
               <head>7</head>
               <l>Haſt thou a frend as hart may wiſh at wil?</l>
               <l>then vſe him ſo to haue his frendſhip ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8</head>
               <l>Wouldſt haue a frend? wouldſt know what frend is beſt?</l>
               <l>haue God thy frende, who paſſeth al the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Poſies for the geastes chamber.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>1</head>
               <l>THe ſlouen and the careleſſe man, the royniſh nothing nice,</l>
               <l>to lodge in chamber comely deckt, are ſeldome ſuffred twice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>With curteine ſome make ſcabert clene, with couerlet their ſho,</l>
               <l>all dyrt and mire ſome wallow hed, as ſpaniels loue to doe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>Though bootes &amp; ſpurs be neuer ſo foule what paſſeth ſom thero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>what place they foile, what thing they teare, by tumbling therupon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>Fowle male ſome caſt on faire borde, be carpet nere ſo cleene,</l>
               <l>what maners careleſſe maiſter hath, by knaue his man is ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>Some make the Chimney chamber pot, to ſmel like filthy ſinke,</l>
               <l>yet who ſo bolde ſo ſone to ſay, fough how theſe howſes ſtinke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>They therfore ſuch as make no force, what clenly thing they ſpil</l>
               <l>muſt haue a kabben like them ſelues, although againſt their will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7</head>
               <l>But gentlemen will gently do, where gentleneſſe is ſhewed,</l>
               <l>obſeruing this, with loue abide, or elſe hence al beſhrewd.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11778:41"/>
            <head>Poſies for thine owne bed <hi>Chamber.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>1</head>
               <l>WHat wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more, what better life, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleaſeth God to ſend</l>
               <l>what worldly goods, what lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger vſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleſeth god to le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>What better fare than wel content, what mirth to quiet welth,</l>
               <l>what better geſt than truſtie frend, in ſicknes and in helth?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>What better bed than quiet reſt, to paſſe the night with fleepe,</l>
               <l>what better worke than dayly care, fro ſinne thy ſelfe to keepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>What better thought than think on God, &amp; dayly him to ſerue,</l>
               <l>what better gift than to the poore, that ready be to ſterue?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>What greater praiſe of God and man, than hatred to forſake,</l>
               <l>what mercyleſſe ſhall mercy get, that mercy none wil take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>What worſe diſpaire than loth to die, for feare to go to Hell,</l>
               <l>what greater faith than truſt in god, through chriſt in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dwel.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:11778:41"/>
            <head>Principall pointes of <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> TO pray to God continually.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> To learne to know him rightfully.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> To honour God in Trinitie,
<list>
                     <item>The Trinitie in Vnitie,</item>
                     <item>The Father in his Maieſtie,</item>
                     <item>The Sonne in his humanitie,</item>
                     <item>The Holy ghoſtes benignitie,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> To ſerue him alway holily.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> To aſke him all thing needefully.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> To praiſe him alway worthily.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> To loue him alway ſtedfaſtly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> To dread him alway fearfully.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> To aſke him mercy hartely.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> To truſt him alway faithfully.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> To obey him alway willingly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> To abide him alway paciently.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> To thank him alway fatherly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> To liue here alway vertuouſly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> To vſe thy neighbour honeſtly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> To looke for death ſtill preſently.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> To helpe the poore in miſerie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> To hope for heauens felicitie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> To haue faith, hope, and charitie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> To count this life but vanitie.
<list>
                     <item>be pointes of Chriſtianitie.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11778:42"/>
            <head>¶ The huſband mannes <hi>belife.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>1</head>
               <l>THis is my ſtedfaſt Creede, my faith and all my truſt,</l>
               <l>that in the heauens there is a God, moſt mighty true &amp; iuſt.</l>
               <l>That made the hanging Skies, ſo deckt with diuers lightes,</l>
               <l>of darkneſſe made the cherefull daies, and all our reſtfull nightes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>That clad this earth with herbe, with trees of ſundry fruites,</l>
               <l>with beaſt, with birde, both wild &amp; tame, of ſtrange &amp; ſundry ſuites</l>
               <l>That intermixt the ſame, with mynes (like veines) of ore:</l>
               <l>of ſiluer, golde, or precious ſtones, and treaſures many more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>That ioyned brookes to Dales, to Hilles freſh water ſpringes:</l>
               <l>with Ryuers ſweete alonges the Medes to profite many things.</l>
               <l>That made the hory Froſtes, the flaky Snowes ſo trim,</l>
               <l>the hony Dewes, the bluſtering winde to ſerue as pleaſeth him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>That made the ſurging Seas, in courſe to ebbe and flowe:</l>
               <l>that ſkilfull man with ſayling ſhippe, mought trauell to and fro.</l>
               <l>And ſtored ſo the ſame, for mannes vnthankfull ſake,</l>
               <l>that euery nation vnder heauen, mought thereby profit take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>That ſendeth thundring claps, like terrors out of Hell,</l>
               <l>that man may know what God it is that in the heauens doth dwell</l>
               <l>That ſendeth threatning plagues to kepe our liues in awe,</l>
               <l>his benefites if we forget, or do contemne his lawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>This is that Lorde of hoſtes, the father of vs all,</l>
               <l>the maker of what ere was made, my God, on whome I call.</l>
               <l>Which for the loue of man, ſent downe his onely Sonne,</l>
               <l>begot of him before the worldes were any whit begonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7</head>
               <l>This entred Maries wombe, as faith affirmeth ſure.</l>
               <l>conceyued by the holy ghoſt, borne of that virgin pure,</l>
               <l>This was both God and man, of Iewes the hoped king,</l>
               <l>and liued here, ſaue onely ſinne, like man in euery thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8</head>
               <l>This was that virgins child, that ſame moſt holy prieſt,</l>
               <l>that Lambe of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet great, whom ſcripture calleth Chriſt.</l>
               <l>This that Meſſias was, of whome the Prophet ſpake,</l>
               <l>that ſhould treade down the ſerpents head, &amp; our attonement make.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:11778:42"/>
            <lg>
               <head>9</head>
               <l>This Iudas did betray to falſe diſſembling Iewes:</l>
               <l>which vnto Pilate being Iudge, did falſely him accuſe.</l>
               <l>Who (through that wicked Iudge) and of thoſe Iewes diſpight,</l>
               <l>condemned and tormented was with all the power they might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>10</head>
               <l>To liuing wight more yll what could ſuch wretches do?</l>
               <l>more percing woundes, more bitter paines, then they did put him to.</l>
               <l>They crowned him with thorne that was the king of kinges,</l>
               <l>that thought to ſaue the ſoule of man aboue all wordly thinges.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>11</head>
               <l>This was the Paſcall lambe, whoſe loue for vs ſo ſtoode,</l>
               <l>that on the mount of Caluerine, did ſhed for vs his bloode.</l>
               <l>Where hanging on the Croſſe, no ſhame he did forſake,</l>
               <l>tyll death geuen him by pearcing ſpeare, an ende of life did make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>12</head>
               <l>This Ioſeph ſeing dead, the body thence did craue,</l>
               <l>and tooke it forthwith from the Croſſe, and layde it in his graue.</l>
               <l>Downe thence he went to hell, in vſing there his will,</l>
               <l>his ſoule I meane, his ſlayed corps, in Tombe remaining ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>13</head>
               <l>From death to life againe, the thirde day this did riſe,</l>
               <l>and ſeene on earth to his elect, tymes oft in ſundry wiſe.</l>
               <l>And after into heauen, aſcend he did in ſight,</l>
               <l>and ſitteth on the right hand there of God the father of might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>14</head>
               <l>Where for vs wretches all, his father he doth praye,</l>
               <l>to take reſpect vnto his death, and put our ſinnes away.</l>
               <l>From thence with ſounded trump, whiche noiſe all fleſh ſhal dread,</l>
               <l>he ſhall returne with glory againe, to iudge the quick and dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>15</head>
               <l>Then ſhal that voice be hearde, come come ye good to mee,</l>
               <l>get you to hell you workers euill where paine ſhall euer bee.</l>
               <l>This is that louing Chriſt, which I my Sauiour call,</l>
               <l>and onely put my truſt in him, and in none elſe at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>16</head>
               <l>In God the holy ghoſt I firmely do beleue,</l>
               <l>which from the father and the Sonne proceding, life doth geue.</l>
               <l>Which by the prophets ſpake, which doth all comfort ſende,</l>
               <l>which I do truſt ſhalbe my guide, when this my life ſhal ende.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>17</head>
               <l>A holy Catholik Church, on earth I graunt there is,</l>
               <l>and thoſe which frame their liues by that, ſhall neuer ſpeede amiſſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11778:43"/>
               <l>The head whereof is Chriſt, his worde the chiefeſt poſt,</l>
               <l>preſeruer of this Temple great, is God the holy ghoſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>18</head>
               <l>I do not doubt, there is a multitude of Saintes,</l>
               <l>more good is done reſembling them, then ſhewing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our plaints.</l>
               <l>Their faith and woorkes in Chriſt, that glorie them did giue,</l>
               <l>which glory wee ſhall likewiſe haue, if likewiſe we do liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>19</head>
               <l>At God of Heauen there is, forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes,</l>
               <l>through Chriſtes death, through faith in it, &amp; through none other gine</l>
               <l>If we (whiles here we liue) repentant mercy craue,</l>
               <l>through ſted faſt hope &amp; faith in Chriſt, for giueneſſe we ſhal haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>20</head>
               <l>I hope and truſt vpon the ryſing of the fleſhe:</l>
               <l>this corps of myne (that firſt muſt dye) ſhall riſe againe afreſhe.</l>
               <l>The body and ſoule euen then, in one ſhal ioyned be:</l>
               <l>As Chriſt did riſe from death to life, euen ſo through Chriſt ſhall we.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>21</head>
               <l>As Chriſt is glorified, and neuer more ſhall dye,</l>
               <l>As Chriſt aſcended is to heauen, through Chriſt euen ſo ſhall I.</l>
               <l>As Chriſt I count my heade, and I a member of his:</l>
               <l>ſo God I truſt for Chriſt his ſake, ſhal ſettle me in bliſſe.</l>
               <l>Thus here we learne of God, that there be perſons three,</l>
               <l>the Father, Sonne, the holy ghoſt, one God in trinitie.</l>
               <l>In ſubſtance all lyke one, one God, one Lorde, one might:</l>
               <l>whoſe perſons yet we do deuide, and ſo we may by right.</l>
               <l>As God the father is, the maker of vs all:</l>
               <l>ſo God the Sonne redemer is, to whome for helpe we call.</l>
               <l>And God the Holy ghoſt, doth make vs pure and clene:</l>
               <l>and moueth vs to waile for grace, we being ouer ſeene.</l>
               <l>This is that God of Gods, whome euery ſoule ſhould loue:</l>
               <l>whome all mens heartes ſhould quake for feare, his wrath on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to moue</l>
               <l>That this ſame mighty God, aboue all other chiefe,</l>
               <l>ſhall ſaue my ſoule from dolefull Hell, is all my whole beliefe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:11778:43"/>
            <head>Of the omnipotencie of God <hi>and debilitie of man.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>1</head>
               <l>O God thou glorious god what god is like to thee,</l>
               <l>what life, what ſtrength is like to thine, as al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world may ſee?</l>
               <l>Thy heauens, thine earth, the Seas, and all thy workes therin,</l>
               <l>do ſhew to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wouldeſt to know what thou haſt euer bene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>But all the thoughtes of man are bent to wretched euels,</l>
               <l>man doth commit Idolatrie, bewitched of the Diuels.</l>
               <l>What euill is left vndone, where man may haue his will:</l>
               <l>man euer was an hipocrite, and euer will be ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>What dayly watch is made, the ſoule of man to ſle,</l>
               <l>by <hi>Lucifer,</hi> by <hi>Balſabub, Mammon,</hi> and <hi>Aſmode.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In diueliſhe pride, in wrath, in couering to much,</l>
               <l>in fleſhly luſt, the tyme is ſpent, the life of man is ſuch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>The ioy that here he hath, is as a ſparke of fier,</l>
               <l>his actes be like the ſmoldering ſmoke, himſelf but dirt and mier:</l>
               <l>His ſtrength euen as a reede, his age like to the floure,</l>
               <l>his breath or life is but a puffe, vncerteine euery houre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>But for the Holy ghoſt, and for his giftes of grace,</l>
               <l>the death of Chriſt, the mercy great, man were in woful caſe.</l>
               <l>O graunt vs therefore Lorde, tamende that is a miſſe,</l>
               <l>and when from hence we do depart, to reſt with thee in bliſſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Th. Thuſſer.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>Note that thoſe ſtaues which be marked with this marke or Paraph (¶) before them, do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to Huſwiferie, &amp; are fitly intermixed with Huſbandrye for the apte tyme and vſe of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:11778:44"/>
            <head>The table to Huſbandrie</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Preface. fo. <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The commoditie of huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie. fo. <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The praiſe of huſbandrie fo. <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Epiſtle to the Lord Paget. fo. <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Epiſtle to the reader fo. <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The deſcription of huſbandrie. fo. <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Ladder to thrift. fo. <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>xxiiii. Leſſons alwaye to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. fo. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for Auguſt. fo. <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for September fo. <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for October. fo. <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for Nouember fo. <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for December. fo. <hi>11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A digreſſion. ſo <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A diſcription of time and the yere. fo. <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of life &amp; ryches. fo. <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of houſekeping fo. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of Chriſtmas. fo. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of apte time to ſpende fo. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt fantaſtical ſcruplenes. fo. <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſtmas huſbandly fare fo. <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for Ianuary fo. <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for February fo. <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for March. fo. <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for Aprill fo. <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for May fo. <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for Iune fo. <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandrie for Iuly, fo. <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The kindlye propertie of euerye Moneth. fo. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A compariſon betwene good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie and euill fo. <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sonet fo. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A compariſon betweene Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion and Seuerall. fo. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The table to Huſwiferie.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Preface fo. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The praiſe of Huſwiferie fo. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lady Paget. fo. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of Huſwife and Huſwiferie. fo. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Twenty Leſſons alwaye to bee obſerued. fo. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A digreſſion of Cock crowning. fo. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſwiferie before breakefaſt or morning workes fo. <hi>29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſwiferie betweene breakfaſt &amp; dinner or fornoone workes. fo. <hi>29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dinner. fo. <hi>32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>After noone woorkes fo. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Euening workes. fo. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Supper. fo. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Workes after ſupper fo. <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Ploughmans feaſting daies fo. <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The good huſwifely Phiſik. fo. <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The good motherly nurſſery. fo. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be trained vp in Muſike. fo. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sonet to the Lady Paget fo. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwene good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiferie and euill. fo. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Huſbandly poeſies for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hall. fo. <hi>39</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:11778:44"/>
               <item>Poeſies for the Parlour. fo. <hi>39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poeſies for the Geaſtes Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. fo. <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poeſies for the bed chamber. fo. <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Principall points of religion. fo. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Huſbandmans belief fo. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the omnipotencie of God, and debilitie of man. fo. <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprynted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>in Fleteſtrete within Temple barre</hi> at the ſigne of the Hand and ſtarre, by <hi>Rychard Tottel. Anno.</hi> 1570.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
